[Music]
Hey,
hey, hey.
[Music]
Down.
Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody.
Namaskar everybody and welcome back to
the Ask a Widget Show. Today we are
doing episode 291. We are talking about
history, Indian history, world history,
all kinds of history. We going to focus
on history today. You all have asked a
lot of questions in the comments and
I've to taken a bunch of those. I'll
answer as many as possible and later
after that I will try and take some
questions from the live chat as well. If
there is time, I suppose there will be
time. So let's do that. But first of
all, let's see who all is there on the
live chat. Let's see who who do we have.
I can see Ganesh Shriant Sugjata Saha
from Singapore. Hello Ashtavakra.
Namaskar Wada Vikas PJ Sakshi Surywanchi
Vish Pala Arush um Aayush Singh chat DSP
Shrih Harun Aditya Kashir Geopolitical
Dubai from Indorin
439 from from Twitch I suppose. Yes.
Hello Krishna from the surmise
Netherlands. Vikash PJ uh Arav Sha
Berserk MMA Ajinka Pawar Bruce Wayne
U Somi Jane Dave Imas Stalin Vladimir
Putin u who else? Shreas D Kumal Sorab
Pranav Soni Priyanchi Sud Tesh Pand
Shashank Koshik Shiva Sai uh who else do
we have? Sunil Seagel
Chetan Radhya
Animals for Laugh from Mumbai. Uh
Himmanshu Kushwahas
Himmanu Kushwah Somia
Somalia Paul one of my first
subscribers. Well, thank you so much.
Good to have you on this live stream. Uh
Arav Shah Jes
good evening ma'am. Ajinkawar
Sarab
Vinit Yadav Namaste Achinti Anand Hello
Rocky Bhai is here. Uh Shria Smith Mitra
from Moscow. Well good evening to you.
Shubat Shukla. Uh Aushin says the first
time of radio chat from Twitch. Been
messaging for a month. I'm sorry. So
sorry. Well I've finally seen it. Good
to have you. Mosh, Anul Sharma
uh and everyone else. Pratik Vora,
Shankr, Mahadevan, Nandi, is Shashi
Kumar, Tanayak Shir, Saga, Vinit, Yadav,
and everyone else. Okay, so let us get
going. Sir Rohit is also here. Have I
watched the Death Note? I may have
watched an episode or two. It was pretty
interesting, but I didn't could not find
the time to watch the entire thing.
Okay, Anime is here. Ashish GK satellite
is also here. Vishpala is my subscriber.
Good to have you ma'am. Vishpali. Very
nice name. I like the name. Very
historical name. A rigidic name, isn't
it? Vishpala.
Okay. All right. So, let's take some
questions. Let's go for Let's go with
the questions. What What's the first
question that I have chosen? Where do we
have the questions? I've got to uh find
the questions. Where are the questions?
Here they are. Let's get going with the
questions. Okay. Okay, what's the first
question? It's by Swapnil Bishra. How
did early humans in the Indian
subcontinent survive the climate
extremes caused by the Toba super
eruption and did it alter their
migration patterns? H interesting
question from more ancient history than
we generally think about. So what is
this Toba super eruption? Let's go to
the map straight away. The first
question takes us to the map. Let us go
to the map and let's discover what this
entire matter is. What is this Tuba
super eruption? So, let's go and search
for Tuba.
Tuba uh not Tuba Tik Singh. Tuba
volcano.
Tuba volcano. Where do we find it's in
Indonesia? It's going to go straight
into it. Mount Tuba.
And
well, here it is, I suppose.
So, as you can see, Mount Toba is
located on an island inside a lake. And
this lake is called Lake Toba. And if
you zoom out, you will see that it is in
Sumatra in Indonesia. So this lake that
you see here, it's actually a volcanic
crater. And there used to be a gigantic
volcano here that erupted with utmost
violence
about 74,000 years ago.
Gigantic, massive volcanic eruption that
that caused a volcanic winter on the
planet. huge massive eruption similar to
um an asteroid impact event like not as
bad as the Chukchulu impact event but
kind of comparable kind of comparable to
uh a nuclear winter which we would never
like to see but yeah so this volcano
which existed here erupted about 74,000
years ago as you can see it's not very
far from the Indian subcontinent not far
at all comparatively speaking so that's
what we're talking about that's the Toba
super volcano eruption happened about
74,000 years ago
Now uh there are archaeological sites in
Andhra Pradesh in northern India as well
where you can clearly see that there is
a layer of ash that is deposited in the
in the ar in the in the in the sediment
layers. And this happens exactly 74,000
years ago, right? And it's and what's
interesting is that you find signs of
human habitation just below the layer of
ash and just above the layer of ash
which means that humans were living in
these regions in Andhra Pradesh
Walapuram or something it's called and
some place in northern India as well at
least two such locations we are aware
of. So humans were living just before
the ash is deposited and just after the
ash is deposited. How do we know humans
are living there? Because you see signs
of human levitation. You see stone tools
and whatever else is associated with
human habitation
which indicates that there were humans
just before this massive eruption
happened and the human presence
continued right after the h the massive
eruption after this deposition of this
layer of ash. So clearly unmistakable
incontrovertible ev evidence that the
same humans continued existing before
and after this super volcanic eruption.
Now what were the consequences of this
eruption? This eruption
expelled incredible amounts of ash
into the atmosphere of our planet. This
was so bad that it c it caused a
volcanic winter which is that the entire
atmosphere was shrouded in smoke and ash
for about a decade. Essentially, this
means there was no sunlight
for a decade. What does that cause? If
there's no sunlight, plants die because
plants need sunlight for photosynthesis.
Plants die out. What happens if plants
die out? The animals that eat plants,
they die out. What happens if animals
that eat plants die out? Animals that
hunt other animals who eat plants. Those
predatory animals die out. Now, what are
we homo sapiens? We are a mixture of a
pred predator and someone who can
subsist on plants. We are omniors,
aren't we? Our ancient ancestors hunted.
They also ate plant-based products, you
know, whatever it was available. So it
obviously would have impacted our
ancestors who lived in the subcontinent
74,000 years ago but they survived. The
question is how did they survive this
disaster 5 to 10 years of no sunlight
freezing temperatures it would have been
snowing in Sri Lanka
that sort of thing that sort of horrific
climate change imagine if it happens
today imagine the impact it'll have and
our ancestors back then they survived
how did they survive? Um we're not
entirely sure what the mechanics and
dynamics were. What we know is that the
Indian subcontinent is a massive massive
region. It's extremely fertile, rich in
um everything that you need to sustain
life. Rivers, forests, there used to be
forests all over the place, plenty of
animals. So our ancestors from that time
would have had to adapt and go into
emergency survival mode. uh this
volcanic winter would not have wiped out
all life on the planet. Maybe 50% of the
species or or vegetation I'm not sure if
species entire species were wiped out
but the population levels would have
dropped drastically by by maybe 60 70
80%. Right? So it would have been a time
of great scarcity. Uh if fish survived
they would have survived on fishing. If
some other animals survived they would
have survived by hunting those animals.
whatever plant matter would have
survived they would have tried to
subsist of that. So essentially they
somehow found a way to stay alive.
One one thing you can do if something
like this happens is you disperse
you disperse over a wider area because
let's say in the past let's say 100
square kilometers was enough to sustain
a population of 10,000 humans for
example hypothetically but now because
of the tremendous scarcity maybe 10,000
people cannot subsist on a 100 square
kilometer area. So you may have to
disperse and spread far and wide so that
there is less need to compete among each
other for survival. So I suppose that
that would have caused migrations within
the Indian subcontinent and and still
the subcontinent was able to somehow
still provide sufficient uh resources
for people who were scattered to survive
to just scrge a living for a decade or
so until the the climate patterns kind
of resumed. the way they used to be
before the volcanic winter. So it would
have been a time of great of great great
uh difficulty
but they survived. That's what we know.
Uh the archaeological record does not
tell us what were the means of survival.
What did they eat at the time? How did
they disperse to what parts of India
they disperse and so on. But they did
survive and that's the only way you can
survive. That's by somehow whatever food
resources are available, you kind of
make do with that. Maybe you shelter
inside caves if it is too cold. If
there's a lot of, you know, dead trees
and all, you use the wood from the dead
trees to to burn to to burn fire so that
you you don't freeze to death in those
freezing conditions. So our ancestors
were extremely resourceful in which and
that's the reason why we we still around
over here. That's what happened. It was
a disastrous event. And it would have
caused catastrophic population declines,
human population declines globally. But
in the subcontinent which was a much
richer area than other parts of the
world, it was easier comparatively
speaking to survive such a disastrous
event. And that's how our ancestors
managed to survive. And once that that
period of about 10 years or so was over,
things started coming back to normal.
This would have impacted climate cycles
for probably several decades, maybe a
couple of centuries possibly. It would
have taken maybe two three centuries for
for the climate cycles to come back
absolutely to the way they used to be
before the super volcano eruption. But
after you survive the first 5 to 10
years and you're still alive, things are
going to be much better for you. So it's
about somehow surviving surviving that
time period. And of course, we humans
are survivors. We have survived all
kinds of disasters in the past. And this
is one of a the prime examples of such a
disaster. So yeah, that's how our
ancestors survived and that's why we are
here today. Uh how did it affect their
migration patterns? We we're not sure
how how it in what way it would have
affected the migration patterns but it
would have caused populations to
disperse far and wide within the
subcontinent itself. And eventually we
know that the subcontinent subcontinent
was the first place where you had the
proper human settlement after the out of
Africa migration because it was so rich.
um in all kinds of resources and it
would have eventually caused you know
more migrations beyond the subcontinent.
Maybe this was one of the triggers. This
event the super volcano um new volcanic
winter may may have been a trigger for
multiple migrations perhaps even out of
the subcontinent eventually.
Swami Mukherji says what was the war so
packed? Was it as effective as NATO? I
feel the USSR was unable to create good
alliances like the west. Hence, it was
quite isolate is isolated. Okay. Um what
was the Warso pact? It was a military
alliance just like NATO and the Warso
Pact alliance emerged as a response to
the formation of NATO. So 1945 the
second world war ends with the nuclear
tests on the civilians of Hiroshima and
Nagazaki and the European portion of the
war had end had ended several months
before that with the collapse of the
Third Reich and the disappearance of
Hitler. Right? Uh so 45 is the dawn the
beginning of a new era of uh human
history. Uh the US was the big winner of
the war. Russia was also a big winner
but the the USSR was also a big winner
but they were devastated by the war.
Devastated. And they had to create this
massive industrial base just to survive
the war and eventually to defeat the
Reich. The US suffered no damage
whatsoever continentally. So the US was
like the big winner. the the baton the
torch had passed from London UK to
Washington DC by this time uh the uh the
US dollar was now the world's reserve
currency and the US in 1949
stitched up the North Atlantic Treaty
Alliance Nate organization North
Atlantic Treaty Organization which is a
military alliance of uh the US Canada
and a whole bunch of Western European
nations to uh
as as as
a a response to the so-called Soviet
threat. So the US is a nation that
espouses democracy and freedom and human
rights. And it says that these values
are universal. These are universal
western values.
Okay, that's what it says. Democracy,
freedom, human rights, all of that.
Considering its impeccable track record,
it should be the flag flag bearer of
these of the of these values. So the US
created the NATO. It first created
something called the Atlantic Charter
with the UK which espoused which
enshrined these rights as universal
values these values as universal values.
In 1949 they created this this military
alliance of all the uh nations that were
kind of under US occupation in Western
Europe to various degrees of uh to
various degrees. And as a response to
that in 1955 the USSR created the Warso
pact which is an a similar military
alliance between between the USSR and
the Eastern European nations. So 1949
you have NATO in response 1955 you have
the Warso pact. Uh this was the USSR and
its vasals just like NATO is NATO is the
US and the American vasals was it it is
what it is. uh I don't warnish things I
I say it as it is. So these are
essentially vasals nothing else. So the
USSR had a bunch of vasals in Eastern
Europe and uh the kind of alliances what
kind of alliances were these? So these
were mutual defense pacts. An attack on
one nation is like an attack on all the
other nations. So they will come
together and fight the the aggressor as
as one group.
That's how it was. Now technically if
you are a member of NATO you can leave
NATO you know technically you can do
that in the Warso pact you could not
leave. So you know if you if you ask
Google or or whatever it is that you ask
what's the difference between the
between NATO and the Warso pack they'll
say NATO was democratic
and the Warsopact was authoritarian.
In NATO you had the ide ideological
difference between the two was that NATO
was democratic. NATO was free and fair.
It was open, transparent. PE a member
state could leave NATO if they wanted
to. The Warso pact was authoritarian. It
was ruled by the USSR. The USSR was the
sole hedgeim and no member member of the
Warso pact could leave.
Did NATO not have a me not have a
hedgeim? So that sort of thing. So that
that so that's the difference.
These were two different ideologies.
Western democracy which is the USR USA
USA style democracy so to say and USSR
style communism and authoritarianism.
These were the two ideological polar
opposites which were you know
represented by these two uh different
blocks. Now how effective was uh the
wars of act? it was just as effective as
NATO. But eventually because of the
decline in standards in the USSR over
the 20th century which led to its
dissolution in 1990 1991 whenever it
happened because of that uh the warsoact
crumbled and eventually it no longer
existed.
U the USSR
obviously did not play the game as well
as the west. the west was able to
essentially encircle the USSR and the
nations within the USSR's uh uh sphere
of control. No question about it. The
the West was able to u to have
essentially all complete access and
control of the oceans. The USSR did not
have that. So that's a different story.
But Warso pact and NATO were both pretty
similar. They they were in opposition of
the other. And while while the Warso act
lasted, it was pretty strong. Eventually
it dissolved right?
Okay. What are the characteristics says
um this question of a civilization? What
are the characteristics of a
civilization and is
uh how can India revert back to being a
civilization and is the west a
civilization? Can we considered the west
to be a civilization?
While the west says that it's a
civilizational entity right they talk
about western civilization and I speak
about India as a civilizational state
that we are not a nation state we are a
civilizational state but am I being
entirely honest when I say that let's
question what I say I keep saying don't
I that India is different from the west
India is a civilization state and the
west is an empire essentially that's
what I say so first of all let let's so
we have to approach this from first
principles. What are the characteristics
of a civilization? So clearly if you
think about it, if you think of all the
great civilizations that have existed in
the past for example, you will know that
a civilization is an advanced society,
right? Clearly a civilization cannot be
um a backward society or whatever. It
has to be an advanced form of society.
Now what are the characteristics of this
advanced form of society? First of all,
I think this is pretty obvious. that
should have a highly evolved indigenous
culture. An indigenous culture that is
institutionalized in the institutions of
the society. So that's the first
characteristic of a civilization. A
highly evolved and institutionalized
indigenous culture. Secondly, if now any
advanced society will have laws, it will
have institutions, right? Uh it may have
a constitution, it may not have a
constitution. But whatever laws exist in
the society, whatever constitution
exists, in case it does, whatever
institutions exist, all of these laws,
institutions, constitution, blah, blah,
blah, all of that has to be necessarily
grounded or based in the indigenous
culture and the indigenous values
of the in of the of the society. So
that's the second requirement of a
civilization. All laws, all
institutions, this constitution,
whatever it is, has to be grounded. It
has to be based in the indigenous
culture, in the indigenous values of the
civilization. Thirdly, you need to have
an indigenous form of governance.
You can't have a form of governance that
is alien to the culture. Right? Next,
you need to have a highly organized
society.
Organized society means a stratified
division of labor,
organized,
institutionalized
that that I mean, if you look at the
Wikipedia page, I suppose of any of of
the word civilization, it will tell you
it's going to have a highly stratified
society, right? So, you're going to have
a highly organized society with division
division of labor and stratification of
society, you know, into various classes,
societal classes. Okay, we're going to
have that. Next you need to have a high
level high degree of societal and
political stability.
The moment your political stability goes
your society starts shake becomes
becomes shaky and the civilization can
disintegrate. So you need a high level
high degree of societal and political
stability. Next this is
this is required. You need to have a
single civilizational language.
You may have lots of languages that
people speak but the civilization has to
be grounded in one language.
So the civilizational language has to be
a single language
that's
that has to be there. So for example if
you look at Greek civilization which is
small you had Greek you had various
versions of Greek and other languages
but you the main civilization language
was Greek. In Chinese civilization you
have the Hanchinese language. Of course
in different parts of China they speak
other languages too but Hanchinese is
the civilizational language. In India it
used to be Sanskrit. Of course in India
you had all kinds of different languages
that people spoke but the civilizational
language was always Sanskrit. Uh next
you need to have a large geographical
area large geography. If it's a tiny
little thing it's not a civilization.
Right? Next you need to have a powerful
economy a powerful military. You need to
have high levels of prosperity. Without
prosperity there is no civilization.
Understand that. If you are living
hand-to-mouth, if there is abject
poverty everywhere, that is not a
civilizational. You can never have high
cultural values and all that in that
sort of society which is reduced to
abject poverty. You need to have high
levels of prosperity. Next, you need to
have a large sphere of economic,
military and cultural influence that
extends well beyond the borders of a
civilization. Which means that a
civilization has to be a next net net
exporter of culture, not a net importer
of culture. A civilization must have its
own scripts of writing. A civilization
needs to have its own calendar, its own
system of timekeeping. It cannot use the
calendar that somebody else gave it. It
must have its own calendarrical system,
its own system of timekeeping. So these
are the characteristics of a
civilization. Now,
okay, there was All right. All right.
Okay. I think we're back. Uh let me just
see.
Is there some lag? Is it frozen? Is the
video frozen? Are you able to hear me
all?
It's interesting that at certain points
in time.
All good now. All good now. I think u
yeah it seems to be back right. It's
good now. So the point is I I think that
I've laid out all the characteristics
that a civilization needs to have.
I did. So now I would like to ask you
all is India is 21st century India
today's India is it really a
civilization?
Right? For example, does India have its
own
does India have an institutionalized
culture?
Do India's laws are India's laws
grounded in our indigenous culture and
in our indigenous values? Are our
institutions
grounded in our culture and our values?
Is India's constitution grounded in
India's culture and India's indigenous
values? Does India have an indigenous
system of governance? H uh does India
have a single civilizational language
today? An indigenous civilizational
language? Um does India have high levels
of prosperity today? Is India a net
exporter of culture today? Does India
have its own scripts today? Does India
have its own indigenous calendarrical
system today? India today
is not a civilization.
India is a colonized culture today.
So if if I keep on saying like I do that
India is a civilization state, I am
actually stretching the truth. I am
giving it some kind of space-time
warping. Yeah, that's the that's the
truth in to be very honest, we are not a
civilization today. Neither is China by
the way. China is not an a civilization
today. either it's it's an empire. It's
trying to ape the US. China is trying to
do whatever it takes to become the next
US. The US is also an empire. India used
to be a civilization until the middle of
the 19th century. Today, we are a
colonized nation even though the
colonizers have left. That's the sad
truth.
But I'll keep saying that we are kind of
kind of still a civilization state. can
still revert to being a civilization
state but we'll have to change a lot of
things and the current system is such
that it doesn't want to change things.
Whoever is in power today they have come
to power because of the kind of system
that we have today. Do you think they
will want to change the change the
system? They will not want to change the
system. They will want to keep the
system the way it is. They will want to
keep this nation colonized and that's
the big problem. So where does the
change come from is the big question.
the way things are we will yeah we will
nothing will
change as of now right okay very
pleasant thoughts isn't it okay okay
this is a question that I was asked
earlier but I kind of missed it so I'll
take it nowan
asked a couple of days ago if archers
crushed heavy cavalry based armies at
Cal and Ajankur why couldn't our archers
Indian archers beat the cavalry based
Turic armies.
Interesting question. That's you know
this is how you you learn how to think.
You know how to think from first
principles. This is how you actually
should should uh you know study history
by asking such questions. Here's
something that happened in the west.
Uh you have these wars between the the
British and the French.
and certain kinds of military tactics
and strategies were used there and those
worked brilliantly.
So why couldn't we use such approaches
here? We also had archers.
We also faced invasions from foreigners
which is the Turks. So if those tactics
worked there, why couldn't those the
same tactics be employed in India? Or
did we employ those tactics? If we
employ those tactics, why didn't they
work? These are the questions, the kinds
of questions you have to ask yourselves
and that's how you actually learn
things. You learn causality, the cause
and effect chain. Okay. So, let's take
this question.
So, English archers, they defeated the
French in Jakur in Calala and so on,
right? And it worked really well. So,
let's let's unpack this. These battles
that used to take place between the
English and the French in Europe, they
typically were pitched battles. The two
armed forces would come together,
they'll find some place to fight and
then they'll fight. Sometimes it would
be ambushes and whatnot. But generally
there were systematic ways of fighting.
You would have the cavalry, you would
have the knights with their heavy armor,
you would have archers, you would have
foot soldiers and so on so forth so
forth. You would have pikemen, you would
have guys with swords and so on. So
every army had a certain set of
components and you knew what the other
army going to is going to have a certain
number of knights who will charge with
big lances and heavy armor on on armored
horses. You'll have pikesmen. You'll
have infantry with swords. You'll have
archers and so on. Now
so these were not very mobile forces.
They would not run around and and wheel
around in in at high speeds. They would
essentially stand face to face and you
would deploy various components of your
armed forces into into the forward areas
into battle phase by phase based on
various tactics and strategies. You
would have flanking maneuvers. You would
have people in reserves hidden hidden
somewhere in the forest who would come
later. That sort of thing. You would try
obviously to catch the opponent by
surprise and defeat them. Now the
English they had something called the
long bow. L O N G long B O W bow long a
bow. This these long bows were typically
around six feet long. The size of a guy.
I mean in those days Europeans were much
shorter. So taller than a man. 6t tall
bows made of a wood called u ye ew. It's
a kind of tree. They're pretty very
strong bows and you need to be you need
needed to be really strong to be able to
uh you know to unleash the arrows from
that and you had pretty long arrows. So
these were pretty innovative weapons.
The French did not have this and you
could uh shoot arrows much at to much
longer distances than with regular
crossbows or whatever. Crossbows are
these little weapons that you hold in
your in your hands.
And you you know you you have crossbow
bolts which are short arrows that you
unleash from there. But long bows were
like totally different weapons and the
French did not have this.
So the English used long bows in for
example the battle of Ajang and they it
is said that they unleashed they they
they shot so many arrows it would darken
the sky
and the arrows would obviously you know
take a parabolic kind of path and come
back and they would devastate the the
the opponent and the French did not have
any answer to that. So this was kind of
a technological innovation that the
English came up with. Now these 6 ft
long bows, they were not highly mobile.
You needed to have let's say 500 guys,
thousand guys, maybe 2,000 guys, 5,000
guys, whatever who were experts in using
this this weapon. They would be
stationed behind your troops and they
would fire from behind. And by doing so,
they would essentially shepherd the
enemy in certain directions. If you if
you launch the arrows in such a way that
they they impact a certain part of the
army, obviously the soldiers will move
away. So you could make you could
essentially shepherd the enemy soldiers
into killing zones where your infantry
and other other parts of the army would
would dispatch them dispatch them to the
next world essentially. So that's the
kind of innovation the English came up
with and uh yeah so that was the long
bow and they they used to pluck the U
that was the deal. So that is what the
English used for a while and that gave
them a super superb military advantage
and they were able to win multiple
battles essentially even decide the
course of entire wars because of this
technological innovation. So that's the
long bow that's what the English used.
Now coming to India. In India the
battles that uh occurred between our
defenders of those times 1100 1200 1300
AD which is essentially the Rajputs what
we now call the Rajputs those those
kingdoms against the Turks. The Turks
were not like the French who would come
with these heavily armored knights with
lances with uh who would be mounted on
heavily armored horses and they did not
have pikesmen and all that. The Turks
had very different battle strategies.
They were very mobile. The Turks were
nomads. They they were very comfortable
in horses. Of course, they would also
have infantry men. Um but their
strategies were different and we did not
have those long bows. Our our our
soldiers from that time the Rajput
armies they would have obviously archers
they would also have swordsmen and all
that. So it was not possible because of
the the nature of the battles to carry
these gigantic bows into battle with
guys who would be stationary because the
battles were highly mobile. The battles
were highly mobile and that's why it was
not really something that would work
against the Turks. The Turks were used
to archery. They they were very adept at
uh you know uh have their tactics were
to have archers on horseback
and they would you know what's called
what's it called the Parthion shot or
whatever which is something the Mongols
also used which is you know shooting
backwards while your horse is charging
this way you'll shoot backwards and so
on. So the Turks already were pretty
proficient with archery and because of
the mobile nature of the Turk war
fighting, it would not really have
worked against them. And if you had,
let's say, 5,000 mobile archers, well,
the Turks could use tactics where
eventually the archers run out of arrows
and then they will be ripe for the
slaughter. So it would not work because
of the way of the nature of the battles
that happened between the Rajputs and
the Turks. So you know it all has to be
contextual. You have to see what kind of
opponent you have and you have to tailor
your battle strategies and battle plans
and tactics based on the nature of the
opponent. If your opponent is not highly
mobile, if they are used to pitch to
battles, if they put all their armed
forces in one place and deploy them, you
know, face to the front, then you can
decimate the rear using archers if
they're not highly mobile and you can
break the ranks. But if they're already
highly mobile and uh in that case it
won't really work. So because of the
different nature of war could not really
work in India.
Amisha Mishra says who were the Seucids
and which countries did the Seucid
Empire control?
Who were the Seucids? Okay. um we may
all remember that uh Alexander the Greek
attempted an invasion of India uh lasted
about 2 3 years 327 to 325 BC right 2 3
years he attempted the invasion it was a
disaster for him he went back uh and he
died in Babylon
what did he die of some say he died of
malaria some say he died of poisoning
some say he died of died of alcohol
poisoning and some say that he may have
died of wounds sustained in battle uh in
India whatever it was he died young.
So Alexander dies um somewhere in the
4th century BC and when he dies his son
is he had this Indian or or Parththeian
or what um Gandharan wife right her name
was Roxana
um so she was pregnant at the time
Alexander died and she eventually gave
birth to a son and that son was
assassinated when he was a teen he never
really took power so Alexander's line
was ended did there and then his
generals they fought among themselves
for power for the control of the al of
the empire that Alexander had won
briefly.
So
he had a number of generals. It was this
this war fighting between his generals
was called the war of the diadeoki the
war of the generals and the general who
came out on top was Salucus Nictor. So
Salucas dictator was able to defeat the
the other generals and he became um he
he founded this new empire. It is now
called the Seucid Empire. So that's the
Seucid Empire and he wanted to expand it
as far as possible. So he went back
eastwards. He came to the borders of
India and he fought this brief war with
the Morian Empire. It was less of a war
and kind of hi I'm here let's shake
hands. That sort of thing. it was you
know I'm around Alexander is gone now
it's me so let's let's come to some kind
of understanding that's the kind of war
it was it was not a very serious war it
lasted a year or two and it ended with a
an alliance between between India and
the Greeks it is the Morian solucid
treaty and it is said that Chandra Gupta
Moria accepted Salucas's daughter as his
wife and uh and to formalize this
matrimonal alliance he uh as as as
counter dowry or whatever he gave
Salucas Nicator 500 war elephants and
Salucas Nicar gave back some territories
that he had usurped from India and that
was the end of the war. It it was the
beginning of an alliance that would last
at least a couple of generations. And
using those 500 war elephants, Salucas
Negger went westwards and he was able to
conquer an empire all the way to Syria
and present day Israel. Huge empire, the
whole of West Asia, all of Persia, all
of Persia.
Syria and also Israel. So all the way to
the to the Mediterranean Sea from the
borders of India all the way to the
Mediterranean Sea. That's how big his
empire was. It included present day
Persia. It included uh Syria, Jordan, uh
present day Iraq,
uh Kuwait, and all those other places.
Not quite the Arabian Peninsula, not
quite that, but all the way to present
day Israel and the shores of the eastern
Mediterranean Sea. That's how large this
empire was. And it lasted
eventually the Salucid Empire also
disintegrated as all empires do. Silucus
nicer dies. His son becomes the emperor.
He also maintains good relations with
with India. And then he has descendants
and those descendants turn out to be not
that great as always. And eventually the
the Armenian Empire takes bites out of
the Seucid Empire and uh various other
kingdoms start taking bites out of it.
And eventually the Romans defeat the
Saluced Empire because the Romans by the
time had had conquered Greece and they
had uh extended their their rule all the
way up to Judea which is Israel and they
eventually destroyed the Seucid Empire.
So that was the deal. That's how it
ended and it was at one point in time a
pretty large empire all the way from the
western borders of India the India Iran
border including Iran all the way to the
eastern Mediterranean Sea. pretty big
big empire
ro a couple of questions here by real
Vladimir Putin and Shub. How did kings
Ashok and Kaneshka spread Indian
culture? Shou says how did emperors like
Ashoka the great and Keshka the great
spread Indian culture and to what extent
did they spread Indian culture? Okay, so
Ashok obviously comes first. Kaneshka
comes a few centuries later. Ashoke was
uh the great unifier of the
subcontinent. The grandson of uh emperor
Chandra Gupta Moria. Ashoke may or may
not have personally known Shar Vishnu
Gupta Chanaka. Possibly as a child you
may have known him but Ashoke took the
empire to its greatest extent. He
unified the entire subcontinent and kind
of you know it was it was a gigantic
empire and a pretty stable empire hugely
prosperous empire strict iron control of
the empire no tolerance for any nonsense
nothing okay and that's how empires have
to be run so Ashok was fantastic was
brilliant he's rightfully called Ashok
the great personally he may have been a
cruel guy or whatever that's okay I
don't care so he did a brilliant job of
unifying the subcontinent and And after
the entire business of fighting and
defeating all the various uh
rebels or whatever after defeating
everybody who could have challenged him
then he became a peaceful guy and he
started spreading dharma. So at the time
you had Buddhism all over India about
the dharma. So he became a great patron
of both the dharma. He did great public
works and he sent embassies to various
parts of the world. He sent uh embassies
to Greece and the embassies would
include large numbers of uh you know uh
bikus and priests and all who would
spread our culture to those parts of the
world. So um so Ashoke says that he had
spread dharma to to Greece which means
he would have sent embassies with with
religious scholars to Greece. He also
um sent embassies to Sri Lanka. his two
of his children, Mahendra and uh what
was the the girl's name? His daughter's
name,
Ashok's daughter, what was her name? The
the the son's name was Mahendra.
Okay, I forget the girl's name, his
daughter's name. But those two siblings,
children of Ashok, they went to Sri
Lanka and they brought with them uh
a sapling that was derived from the
original Bodhi tree. It was planted in
Sri Lanka. It still exists today. The
same tree sangra Mahindra and Sangapitra
they were they were the two children. He
had many children but two of those were
Mahindra and Sangapitra. They went to
Sri Lanka and they spread dhamad and Sri
Lanka till today is mainly mostly
Buddhist right it's a Buddhist maj
majority country. Ashok also spread
Dharma to Surabumi which is Thailand and
uh mostly Thailand and Southeast Asia.
uh so he did all he could to spread our
culture far and wide all across the
neighboring uh parts of the world. So
that's what Ashok did and he also you
know funded and financed the
construction of all kinds of temples and
monasteries and viharas and mahavir
biharas and whatever else he could do.
He was a very generous king and he was a
great patron of our culture and he did
his best to spread our culture beyond
the physical boundaries of the Indian
subcontinent. So there is Ashok
Kaneshka. What about Kaneshka? So
Kaneshka was a descendant of immigrants.
He was a descendant of Tushara kings.
The Tusharas were the Tokari in English
they called the Tokarians. They lived in
the Sinjang region, the Tarin basin
region. That's where they originated as
far as we know. Obviously, they would
have originated somewhere else beyond
that. How did they arrive in Singinjang?
We're not quite sure. But you still find
mummies of these people there in the
Tarim Basin region. They are called the
Tarim Basin mummies or something. And if
you look at the the mummies, they are
white-kinned and they generally have
blonde or red hair. But their genetics
are R1 A1A, the male genetics, which is
exactly the same as most Indians. So,
interesting thing. Um and the tokaran
language was a satam sentum language not
the satim language which is like two
divisions of the indo-uropean language
family and the gods they worshiped the
tokarans were our gods so very
interesting combination so those are the
origins of the tushara people the kusans
eventually the Chinese called them the
UAE and eventually they came to be known
as the Kushans
so the Kushans had to flee from the
Hunik expansion which came out of
Mongolia and flee. By fleeing they had
to displace the the skitians from
wherever they were and they eventually
the Kosans eventually started settling
down in in the northwestern parts of the
subcontinent and u they expanded their
kingdom gradually by displacing the
Indo- Greeks and eventually you have the
birth of Kaneshka who went on to be the
greatest of the emperors of the Kushan
Empire and one of our greatest emperors
ever and his empire encompassed much of
northern western India parts of Deaken
also he had two capitals. One was
Matura, one was Purushpur which is
present day Peshawar
and uh through through Matura he he he
was able to administer the Indian
subcontinent all of it whatever parts he
controlled which was the majority of it
and through Peshawar he was able through
push pushpour he was able to administer
uh central Asia. So understand the the
size of Ganeshka's empire.
The maps that you will see they will not
tell you the entire story. He
he had um he he ruled over northern,
western, central India all the way up to
Patutra. Patutra was part of his empire.
So eastern India as well. Not sure about
Assam and the far east states of India
today. Not definitely not southern India
but all of that part of India and
Kashmir. He was very fond of Kashmir.
Kaneshka was was in love with Kashmir
for some reason. There is a there is a
town called Kaneshkapur in Kashmir. It
is called Kaneshpur or something today.
So he he was in love with Kashmir for
some reason. Kaneska maybe he spent his
childhood there. I'm not really sure.
And he his empire also stretched from
the shores of the Caspian and Arali all
the way to Shinjang present day
Singinjang in in currently part of China
gigantic empire.
And through that he because of that he
controlled all the trade between India
and China in the east and Rome in the
west. He controlled all of that. He was
the middleman. He took taxes for both
ways and he became his empire became
enormously rich as a consequence which
is our land became enormously rich rich
as a consequence. Um and he was a great
patron of culture. Dur during his rule
two different schools of culture
essentially thrived in the subcontinent.
One is the Matura school of arts. the
Matura style of of sculptures
very unique and distinctive style the
Matura style uh that's one and the other
one is the Gandhara style the the
depictions of Buddh buddha in the
helenistic fashion the Gandhara style so
two very different schools of art they
thrived during the time of kaneshka and
he obviously was the was the patron of
all of that he gave uh whatever funding
financing was needed for all for all of
this he was obviously enormously
wealthy. His empire was incredibly
wealthy and he patronized all the
different
religious manifestations that existed in
India and central Asia. Whether it is
the both the dharma, whether it is the
shvite dharm, whether it is the vehnawad
dharm, whether it is zorastrinism,
whether it's whatever he was the the he
was the patron of everything. Okay. He
he encouraged all all these different uh
manifestations of of dharma or whatever
it is. And
obviously at that time still Buddhism
both the dharma was still the ma the
major uh dharmic form that was prevalent
in the subcontinent.
So uh he was that's why he was also a
big patron of of what we call Buddhism
today. And he used to send embassies
he see his empire was a trading empire.
He also controlled the great ports in
Sawashtra in western India that traded
with Rome. So whenever he would send a
trade delegation wherever he made sure
that he would send religious persons
with with those people essentially
religious gurus and teachers and
whatnot. It may not have been that
successful in the west because the west
never became Indianized. Rome never
became Indianized. Right? You do find
you do find examples of of Indian um
Indian contact over there. For example,
the Lakshmi of Herculanium. So you do
find archaeological evidence of the
presence of Indians in Rome. But Rome
never adopted Indian religion. Maybe it
was just too far away. But he sent all
these trade delegations and embassies to
China. And through those he he sent
dharmic gurus uh both the big shows and
both the scholars and people who would
be learned in the Vedas and whatnot. And
because of Kaneshka's activities, the
whole of China eventually became
Indianized. Kaneshka is the man who did
that. Kaneshka.
And through China, it spread to Korea,
it spread to Japan, it spread wherever
else, Mongolia, wherever else. So,
Kaneshka is the man who was instrumental
in Indianizing the whole of East Asia.
Tremendous. I mean, the kind of work he
did tireless and tremendous. He was in
power for like 20 30 years. That's it.
And then he we don't know what happened.
He died and his son Huishka became the
emperor. So, Kaneshka was this guy super
vigorous guy. His entire life was like
expans expanding his empire defeating
one guy after the other. He even
defeated the Parththeians and took some
of bites of the territory because why
not that thing but apart from the the
expansionist tendencies that he have
that he had he was this great great
patron of culture and he was this great
spreader of Indian culture especially
eastwards and through the actions of one
man the whole of China essentially
became Indianized over time but he is
the guy who started all of that and then
after after his death and even after the
dissolution of the of the Kushan Empire
the Chinese used to send embassies to
India to the Gupta emperors asking for
more scholars. Please send us more
scholars with more Sanskrit sutras that
they can translate into Chinese. So the
this entire process was started by
Kaneshka great man uh one of our
greatest emperors ever if not our
greatest emperor. So some people said
that Kaneshka was was a foreigner. He
was a descendant of immigrants. I mean
what what was his culture? What did he
do? Whose culture did he did he promote?
Whose culture did he spread the
worldwide?
our culture right did he see himself as
a foreigner really if he saw himself as
a foreigner would he do that I don't
care what what blood you may have the
anywhere the Kushans the tusharas were
of Indian ancestry they themselves in in
tarim in the tarim region river region
they used to practice our culture there
itself right uh so yeah I don't see
kaneshka as as a foreigner what utter
nonsense utter nonsense kanka was one of
the one of the greatest Indians of all
time
Okay.
Uh, Shub says, "Please tell us about the
Mitani dynasty and its role in debunking
the ar picnic theory." Uh, the Mitani
dynasty, the Mitani Empire.
U so there is
in Syria there are all these
archaeological sites. Okay.
In the 20th century, there were with
these western archaeologists who were
excavating
uh what was it? Was it Hatusa? Maybe a
place called Hatusa.
Um which was one of the major sites, one
of the major cities of the
Mitani Empire possibly and they were
excavating. And they found very stone
tablets and they they deciphered the
stone tablets and it gave them the shock
of their life because it was a peace
treaty between the Mitani and the
neighboring kingdom, the Hurans. I
believe the Mitani and the
the Hittites,
the Mitani kingdom and the Hittite
kingdom. A peace treaty.
It was in the Huran language. But when
you do a peace treaty, you have you need
to have great divine witnesses, right?
That this treaty is blessed by the gods
and so on. So as the divine witnesses,
you had the names of Mitra, Vuna, Indra,
all that. So there was the shock of
their life. I mean they this is a peace
treaty between the Hittites and the
Mitani in in one of the major cities of
the Mitan Mitani. And you have this
treaty being blessed by the the Aryan
gods Mitra, Vuna, Indra, etc. So, how on
earth is that possible? Then they they
did more more excavations and they found
this horse trading manual, a horse
trading manual, a manual for how to take
a regular horse and train that horse
into a war horse that can fight battles.
It's a it's a stepbystep what multiple
monthlong manual that on day one you do
this with your horse. Day two you do
that each day exactly what to do, what
to feed the horse, how many uh circles
of the of the the of the racetrack he
should take, what what he should drink,
what what he know he should not eat the
horse and exactly day by day it's a
breakdown of how how to convert a
standard regular horse into a war horse,
a horse breeding manual in the Huran
language. But once again when you
deciphered that there are certain
shocking things because the Huran
language did not have specific
terminology
spec words for specific scientific
terms.
So the guy who wrote this training
manual his name was Kikuli Kikuli the
mitani he had to introduce terms in a
foreign language for those technical
terms. Navana nine rounds of the
racecourse of the horse track right
Navana and and various other Sanskrit
terms he had to use because those terms
did not exist in the Mitani language. So
a whole bunch of Sanskrit terms are used
in this Huran language horse training
manual by Kikuli the Mitani. So Kikuli
tried his best to write this horse
trading manual in the local language but
some words did not exist. That's why he
had to use his own language
for those scientific terms for those
technical terms. So once again you have
a guy who was a high status horse
trainer who was using Sanskrit terms
because the terms do not exist exist in
this language. So eventually it became
clear that the Mitani Empire
was it was located in Anatolia and Syria
but its elite were Sanskrit speakers and
Hindus essentially Indo-arians Indians
arians right so the aristocracy and the
royalty was Indo-arian but the common
people were the Horeian speaking local
uh local people so that was the Mitani
Empire
And they had kings who had proper
Sanskrit names Tesha, Rata and whatever
the names are. And these kings also had
extensive diplomatic correspondence with
the Egyptian pharaohs. There is
something called the Amara letters in
which you have multiple letters that are
sent by
the king of the Mitani to the king of
the Egyptians and there's this back and
forth between the king the two kings and
then the the pharaoh dies. So the Mitani
kings sends a letter to the widow of the
pharaoh continuing the correspondence
and then the widow's son becomes the
next king. So he continues the
correspondence with the next king that
sort of thing.
So this was an big empire very strong
powerful empire very rich empire it was
ruled by Indoarians by people of Indian
ancestry and if you look at the Sanskrit
terminology that is used it is late vic
is not rigidic it is late vic
terminology.
So how did this happen? Does does it
mean that these were the Arians who then
invaded India? Does it mean that? Does
it really mean that? Uh no, not quite.
These were and and at the same time
where you have the emergence of this Hit
Mitani Empire and the next door you had
the Hittites who also had an Indian
aristocracy, an Indian ruling class,
right? Mitani Kingdom, Hittite Kingdom
both have local people who speak local
languages. But the ruling class, the
royalty is Indian in both cases. Right?
And this is about 1,500 BC. About 3 and
a half thousand years before today.
About 500 years before that, before the
emergence of the of the Mitani Kingdom
Empire,
500 years before the emergence of the
Mitani Empire, you have the sudden
introgression
of a specific animal into West Asia.
What is that animal? It is the Indian
zebu cattle. The cattle with the big
humps, big humped cattle which you see
in the Indas Saraswati region, seals,
those big bulls with the big humps,
those cattle suddenly emerged, suddenly
appeared in West Asia. 500 or so years
before the emergence of the Mitanian
Hittite empires and that's that's around
2,000 BC that the cattle appear in West
Asia. At the same time, these cattle
also appear in Egypt.
So cattle Indian origin cattle which
which originated in India nobody can
disprove that this is a fact the zebu
cattle originated in the subcontinent
and cattle were domesticated cattle
don't decide one morning okay let's go
to let us let us uh go to a m do a
migration we will go to west Asia cattle
don't decide that cattle do whatever
their masters tell them so this
indicates that Indians traveled to west
Asia around 200 BC with cattle and
settle
And eventually you had the rise of these
empires, Mitani and Hittite empires.
This is out of India migrations
thousands of kilometers west of India.
Now is this attested in um in Indian
literature. There is a late Vic text
called the Bodhana
Sutra. Bodhyana Sutra. Let's let's
Wikipedia, shall we? Let's Google it.
What does Wikipedia have to say about
the Baana Sutra? What does it have to
say? Let's see.
Bodhaana
Sutra. There we have it. Religious text,
right? What does Wikipedia have to say?
It's a late Vic text dealing with blah
blah blah composed in Eastern Utar
Pradesh because they know exactly where
it was composed, right? These geniuses.
Uh what does it say? Bodhana wrote the
sutra. Okay. Kvas school whitewa
and so on. Um etc. translation
controversy. According to Michael
Vitzel, this genius here, German
American philologist, Indologist,
according to this genius, some passages
in this uh sutra point to the Indo-arian
migrations, no longer invasion, now
they're saying migrations. And uh
so he essentially
translated mistransated this saying that
Amawasu went eastwards not Aayou it is
Amawasu
okay but he del and Rmula Tapar also
supported what he says but if you know
anything about Sanskrit you will realize
that it is not eastwards it's a westward
migration that he's talking about okay
so it says that Amawasu migrated
westwards
and his people are the Arata, the
Gandhara and the somebody else.
So Arata we don't know but Gandhara we
clearly know yeah the Gandhara the Para
and in the Arata these are the people of
Amavasu according to this text the
Gandhara people obviously it's Gandhara
obviously it's it's right here northwest
India Afghanistan that's Gandhar
everyone knows what that is Pu Pashu
people Paru people Persia obviously
Arata could be Armenia Mount Ararat
perhaps we don't know for sure but
clearly this is evidence of a westward
migration of ancient Indians during the
late Vic age whenever it happened. We
don't know quite when it happened. They
say it's 10,000 BC or something which is
nonsense. So these people Michael Witzel
and whatever they have been trying
to obiscate history. They've been trying
to say that you know these are this is
evidence of eastward migration which is
a lie. It was a westward migration that
was referenced in it. So if you put all
these different pieces of evidence
together you can see that there were
migrations of India which were recorded
in literature and these migrations went
westwards.
Uh and yeah, so this obviously pokes
gigantic holes in this Arian
invasion/migration
theory that these people love so much.
Amisha says, "Why did Burma stay
Buddhist and reject Christianity and
Islam if European Christian min
missionaries were successful in Eastern
India?"
Interesting question. Um
first of all we have to ask ourselves
ask ourselves when did this Christian
missionary start becoming successful in
eastern India
when we talk about eastern India we're
talking about far east right now which
is what what most people think of as the
northeast of India it's the far east of
India it's not the northeast
geographically so when did the Christian
missionaries become start becoming
successful in the far east of India in
the 20th century
uh if you look at 1900 for example there
were hardly any convert converted
Christians in India's far east even in
Nagaland by 1940 there may be some Nagas
who were converted to Christianity
but by 2000 most Nagas are converted to
Christianity that their indigenous
culture has been destroyed and uh now
they are going after Arunachal Pradesh
they're trying to destroy whatever is
left of Manipur and Misoram is whatever
it is so this process happened during
the 20th century it intensified after
1947 because of Nehu because of the
magnificent Mr. Neu who said that we
have to convert northeast to
Christianity to civilize it
because according to Mr. and a
Christianity is civilized and anything
else is not. So, so this is something
that happened mainly in the 20th
century. And when we're talking about
India's far east, across the border we
have Burma. Did the the Christian
missionaries try the same in Burma? They
did. They tried this all across
Southeast Asia.
Before we deal with Burma, let me talk
about Vietnam. Okay, let's let's briefly
talk about Vietnam. See the Christian
missionaries they always go after
isolated population groups, tribal
population groups who are not part of
the mainstream because people who are in
the mainstream in in East Southeast Asia
and India they they are civilizationally
very strongly rooted. For example,
Vietnam, Southeast Asia, there have been
there is Hinduism, Buddhism that goes
back at least 2,000 years. People are
very deeply rooted in this. And if you
if you bring a foreign religion like an
Abrahamic monotheistic religion, these
people will laugh at you in your face.
What the hell are you trying to trying
to foist on us? We don't need this.
That's what they will say. So the the
missionaries decided not to target the
the the Buddhist practitioners and Hindu
practitioners. They went after tri
isolated tribal communities who were
easier to to to convert, who were easy
to impress.
The the the people of Southeast Asia or
India initially would have seen the
Europeans as inferior,
coming from an inferior culture. You may
be great at violence and ruling, but
your culture is inferior. That's what
that's how we would have seen them. But
people who lived in isolation, they
would have thought of these people as
gods. So they were the they were easy to
convert. So for example, if you go to
Vietnam, you have a people called the
Mana which is the mountain people in
French
Vietnam
mot.
So the Mana people is an umbrella term
for the various indigenous peoples of
the central highlands of Vietnam. You
know once again they use the term
indigenous people to to imply that the
other people of Vietnam are are somehow
invaders or something. Yeah. Anyhow, so
you have all these uh various ethnic
groups and they have been used
uh to fight various civil wars and whatn
not. Okay. And if you see you will find
that lots of these people these isolated
people were converted to Christianity.
For example,
Catholic church, Catholic church,
Motanyak churches, churches, churches
all that you can see there's a lot of
that. What is the evang evangelical
church of Vietnam? Uh Protestants are a
minority in Vietnam constituting 1% of
the population. But it is the country's
fastest growing religion now. It's
growing at 600% per year in the early
2000s and
once again the growth of Protestantism
has been most dramatic among ethnic
minority peoples like the Mana etc. So
that's the game the the missionaries
play. Now when it comes to when it comes
to Burma okay let's see Burma religious
demographics.
Okay, let's see what is the percentage
of Christianity is 6.2%. It is not
small. It is not small. Right now, let's
see where is Christianity more
widespread. Chin state, Kachin state,
Kaya state. Where is Chin state by the
way? Shall we shall we find out where is
Chin state? Let's see.
It is the region that is right next to
Manipur and Misoram.
It is where the cookies are infiltrating
into India from. There you have 85%
Christianity.
Please understand the patterns. It all
adds up slowly.
So even if you go to places like Laos,
Vietnam, the missionaries always
targeted these these people who
who lived in isolation who lived in the
hills in the mountains. Chin state is
full of hills and mountains in Burma. So
you go and target those people. You
convert them to Christianity. And then
you slowly spread that over time. You
can the missionaries are happy to wait
decades even centuries for this to
spread slowly. So now in Burma
Christianity is about 6%. In Kachin
state Chin state is about 85%. Chin
state is right next to Manipur. Manipur
is a small Hindu majority region. Only
the central part of Manipur the the
valley part of Manipur is Hindu
majority. Even there the indigenous
people are now being converted to
Christianity. So slowly they want to
take everything over.
So that is the deal. Understand the
patterns, understand how it has happened
over time. This I can make I can do a
two-hour episode actually about this but
it is best I don't know don't do that.
Okay.
Yajj Navalia says, "Historically, what
are the mechanics and dynamics of elite
imposition of if any of a language
of a tiny u ruling minority on a large
population consist composed mainly of
illiterate farmers. Here imposition is
intended to mean complete change of the
population's mother tongue. Okay. Elite
imposition. You have a tiny ruling
minority. You have a large population
who are mainly farmers or whatever
illiterate and how does it happen? Is it
even possible for this to happen?
Is is is it possible for a tiny majority
ruling majority a tiny ruling minority
to completely change the language over
time of a large population? Interesting
question for okay let's take some case
studies.
We discussed the Mitani just now. The
Mitani Empire 1500 BC to about 1200 BC
around that time give or take roughly.
So you have the Mitani Empire and and
the the majority population is the
locals who speak the Huran language
and the ruling class the royalty and
aristocracy they speak Sanskrit. They
come from they came from India. So
you've got a tiny ruling majority who
speaks Sanskrit and practices Hinduism
and they are ruling over a huran
speaking group of people. What happened
eventually? Sanskrit never became the
mainstream language in Mitani society.
It never did but some cultural
influences persisted even after the
dissolution of the Mitani Empire. So
it's because of the kind of religion and
culture India has that even if they've
went and conquered this foreign land and
ruled over it, they never sought to
impose their culture on the locals.
They never tried.
Kikuli the the horse trainer wrote a
manual not in Sanskrit but in the Huran
language. He only introduced a few words
in Sanskrit. Sanskrit which did not
exist in the Huran language. So he tried
his best to adapt himself to the culture
of the locals.
Um but when you had a peace treaty
between two kingdoms that were ruled by
Indians there it's there there you had
the the invocation of the the the Vic
deities Indra Mitrauna etc. But the
Mitani rulers never tried to impose
their Sanskrit language and their Hindu
religion on the locals. They never did
that because otherwise this whole region
would have been Hindu, Hinduized. You
don't see that. It never happened. Um
but you do find some hymns that were
written in the Huran language that have
the same same rhythmic pattern as
Sanskrit as as rigidic verses. So
somehow the culture kind of remained
behind and huran religious hymns took on
the the meter and and uh rhythmic
patterns of rigidic verses. So it kind
of had this effect but it was never done
by force. So here you will see an
example of a ruling class that did not
impose anything by force.
That's one example. Second, let's take
Anatolia, which is again the same region
that the Hurans that the Mitani ruled,
right? Anatolia, which is eastern
Turkey. The 90% of Turkey is Anatolia,
which is also called Asiatic Turkey. It
used to be Greek in the past. So,
Anatolia
in the second millennium AD, the Turks
invaded Anatolia, which was mostly which
was an entirely Greek and Armenian land.
So the local population was Greeks and
Armenians. At that time they were
Christians. So the Turks invade and you
have the Byzantine Empire there. The
Turks over the centuries over over a
couple of centuries they destroy the
Byzantine Empire and eventually they
create this Ottoman Empire and the
subjects are Greeks and Armenians.
And if you look at the region today,
everyone speaks Turkish, everyone is
Muslim. What happened there? It was
imposed by force.
imposed by force. This was done
forcibly. The language was imposed by
force. The religion was imposed by
force. And they had this practice of
abducting women and marrying them to
their men. And that's how the entire
genetics all that changed. And today, if
you look at the Turkish people, the the
average Turkish person would have about
95% Greek or Armenian genetics. Hardly
5% at most Turk genetics, but culturally
they're entirely Turk.
So this was done through the sword.
So the Indians who ruled the region
Anatolia as part of the as the rulers of
the Mitani Empire and Hittite Empire,
they never did that. They chose not to
do that. It was a cultural choice. We
don't it's not part of our culture to to
force somebody to to to change their way
of life. The Turks, they said it's part
of our culture and we're going to do it
to you. So So it's done by force. If it
happens, it is only because it is done
by force. Uh similarly Egypt, it used to
speak the Egyptian language. I mean the
people of Egypt spoke the Egyptian
language. They had their own culture,
their own religion. Today if you go to
Egypt, they consider themselves to be
Arabs. They speak the Arabic language.
And there is not a shred of original
Egyptian culture or language that
survives. How did this happen? Through
force, through the sword.
Let's come to India.
You had the British in India, right? The
British ruled India. First you had the
Turks. Let's let's talk about the
British. So the British ruled India for
two and a half centuries. They left in
1947 so to say
today if you look at India
uh their religion is kind of growing in
India now the British the Christianity
is growing in India
uh because of a tremendous influx of
money and so on and India's official
language is kind of English now because
of our our colonized leaders have
continued those British practices. So
how did English became the main become
the main language of India? How did
English become the mainstream language
of India? Today if you want to have a
good job that pays you a few lakhs a
month, you need to speak really good
English.
They won't even tolerate you in the
interview room if you don't speak decent
enough English. You will never get a
high paying job in India if you don't
speak high quality English. That's
what's been done to India today. Right?
It's English a path essentially. How did
this happen? It's first of all the
British destroyed the Indian education
system. That's one of the things the
mechanics and dynamics. They destroyed
the Indian Indian education system. They
disestablished the Indian education
system. They de-industrialized India and
popularized India. And then they ensure
that any job if you want to have which
will give you a decent monthly income so
that you survive, it can only come
through the government, the British
Indian government. And for that you have
to be educated through the British
imposed education system which was all
about learning the English language and
having good handwriting and being
completely obedient. And that's how they
they did this and this has been
continued through the 20th century even
now in the 21st century. So it's it's
brainwashed generations of Indians into
into having certain mindset a certain
kind of mindset a slave mindset a
mindset of this this deep inferiority
complex and this belief that English is
a superior language. Right now Sridar
Wambbu and Zoho have come up with this
new app, right? It's called Aratay. It's
a messaging app. If you go on Twitter
today, you have all these genius Indians
who are saying that we need to change
the name of Aratai.
It has to be something that the West
will understand.
These these are these Indians are are
are brilliant examples of inferiority
complex
ridden mentally colonized people. And
it's not regular Indians who are saying
this. It's very prominent people who are
saying this that Aratai needs to be
renamed to something the world will
understand idiots. So this is how it
happens you see.
Okay. Hy penguin says how come the
Romans could not conquer Gmana Magna
easily
considering the region was noti was not
united and the local tribes would fight
each other all the time. Similarly why
did the Chinese not conquer the Mongol
tribes before Chingishan happened and
why did they let Chingan unite the
tribes? Why did the both these powers
like the Romans and the Chinese choose
to engineer fights between the tribes
but could not conquer the tribes?
Why engineer fights among them? Why not
just conquer the land and rule the land?
Well, there has to be something
worthwhile in the land to conquer. Let's
go to the map. We'll talk about Gmana
Magnda first. What is Gmana Magda? It's
the present day land of Germany. Okay.
What's called Germany today? Where did
the name Germany come from? It came from
Germania
Latin. Gmania magnum means great
Germany. So
we're talking about Germany. Essentially
Germany is a newly formed artificial
nation. By the way, it was formed in
1871. Before that there was no Germany.
So this region is what the Romans called
Gmana Magna. Switzerland was part of
what they called Gaul. North and east of
Gaul you had Gmana. Gmana Magna. Now see
the the Romans conquered the whole of
Gaul which is France and Switzerland.
Why did they conquer it? It was full of
fertile land, great agricultural land.
The Gaul had had a large population and
you could make the population work. You
could make them do agriculture. You
could collect great amounts of taxes
from them and you could you could you
know bring them into the armed forces or
use them as slaves. So and so many other
uses for these people in their land. So
the entire land of France which was
called Gaul and Switzerland, it was very
valuable for Rome. It was a source of
great riches. So was Iberia.
Very valuable land. Tremendous riches
from there. They also got a lot of gold
gold the metal from uh from Iberia. But
when it comes to Gmania, Germany, it was
this land that was full of forests,
a heavily forested land. You had forests
all over the place. You had hills all
over the place. And you had small
population groups, tribes that were
scattered all over the place.
There were no great resources available
in Germany.
Swampy marshy terrain, streams and
rivers all over the place, hills
everywhere and forests and wild people
living in small tribal groups. How do
you conquer these people? You go and
attack them. They will just disperse
into the forest for months disappear.
What do you do?
How do you conquer them?
And there are no big cities,
not even towns, just scattered villages.
And there is there are no resources
there that can make your empire rich. It
will cost you way more to administer the
land
than so it's it's and and you will get
nothing out of it. So it is a net
negative for the empire to to conquer
and administer the administer the land
first of all can't be conquered unless
you deforest the whole land which is
which will take so much manpower and so
much time why do that right so that's
why they never bothered to conquer gab
they tried a few times and then they
realized it's it's not worth our time
right and of course they did face some
setbacks like uh the battle of Tutubberg
forest which was one of the few times
the Germanic tribes united under
Armenius who was a German but who who
had been who who who had learned the
Roman ways because they lived in Rome
for a while. So that's that was in 10 AD
or something the battle of Tutubberg
forest and there was a disaster for
Rome. But eventually so what the Romans
decided that is that we will not conquer
the land. We will not administrate.
We'll just keep them fighting each other
so that they don't become a nuisance for
us. Keep them divided. Keep them
fighting each other. Let it go on and we
will just uh you know ensure that they
don't spill over into the territories we
control. So it did not make sense for
them to conquer this land and administer
it because they would get nothing out of
it. If you don't have a population of
several millions, how do you collect
taxes, if you are not getting taxes,
then you're spending more on ad on on
administration and you lose soldiers
here and there? It's not worth your
time. That's why they did not bother to
conquer Gmana Magna. They gave up
eventually. They said, "It's not worth
our time. It's not worth the headache."
That's why Rome said, "Okay, we don't
need Gmana Magna." Now, similarly, why
did the Chinese not conquer the Mongol
tribes? Once again,
Mongolia's population was what? A
million, 2 million? Spread across a
gigantic territory. Population density
next to nothing. Nothing. What could you
What could the Chinese get out of
Mongolia? What resources? Would they get
gold? Would they get timber? Would they
get something of value? Nothing. It's
empty land from from a Chinese
perspective, from a Mongol perspective,
it's their sacred homeland. And they
knew how to live in in in that land.
They knew how to how to subsist of the
land. For the Chinese, there was nothing
of value in Mongolia. Nothing at all. So
why why bother to conquer the land?
It'll take so much time, resources,
energy, effort, and money to administer
the land which is empty.
And the tribes once again will disperse
whenever they when whenever they are
challenged. They'll dis disperse and
disappear for weeks or months. And then
they will come back and and again attack
you. guerrilla tactics, ambush tactics.
Why waste your time over that? It's not
worth your time. That's why the Chinese
decided that we will not conquer
Mongolia.
We will simply keep the Mongols fighting
each other.
Okay? And that's why they had this
policy for centuries.
Sow division among the Mongols. Keep
them fighting each other. Keep punishing
them from time to time with punitive
raids. Capture their leaders, execute
them, torture them, whatever. do it from
time to time to to send the message to
the Mongols that China is not to be
messed with. You stay in your land and
the Chinese would keep them fighting
each other. They would send one
ambassador to one tribe, another to to a
different tribe and create enmity,
create hostility. Then you have to play
the politics and that's how the
Mongolians kept fighting each other for
centuries. Now why did the Chinese allow
Chingaskhan to unite to unite the
tribes? This unification of the tribes
happened over a very short period of
time. 20 years
before the Chinese knew anything. It had
happened 20 years is a very short period
of time.
Actually speaking, geopolitically
speaking, the Chinese always had this
conception that the Mongols are a bunch
of rag tag idiots. We know how to deal
with them. We'll keep them we'll keep
them fighting each other. We have
ambassadors here and there and we'll
just keep it going. They had no idea
that in a short period of 20 years
Mongolia will turn into a ginormous
beast and and essentially eat China
alive. So it happened before they
realized what was happening. One fine
day the Mongols turn up at your doorstep
and then what do you do? That's what
happened.
Yajjnalia says, "Did the religion
founded by the prophet Zaratustra have
an influence on the theology of the
second temple Judaism during the time of
the Aimeirate Empire's rule over
Babylonia, Judea and Israel?"
Okay.
So, you had the first temple that was
founded by Solomon, the temple of
Solomon, right? Uh Solomon lived around
900 AD, 900 BC or thereabouts, somewhere
around that time. And he had built this
big temple. Uh and then the Jews
uh they were conquered by Nabuku
Kudrachar
of Babylon. What what did I say? Nabuku
Kudrachar. What is that? Nabuked Nazar
is what the British or the English like
to call him. Let's Google this. Nebu
Nazar II.
So if you Google the guy's name, it will
say Nebuchadnezzar.
See
Nabu Kadnazar.
Nabu Kadnazar. His actual name was
Nabu
Nabu Kudrachar. That's what the Persians
called him. Nabu Kudrachar. But the the
British the English have to call him
Nabukad Nazar because you have to mangle
all indigenous names. Right. Anyhow,
Nabukudrachar II was the great ruler of
Babylon, okay, of the Babylonian
dynasty. And he had conquered Judea. He
had conquered the Jewish lands.
When did this happen?
597 BC.
589 BC. Around that time, there were two
two conquests. And after the second
conquest, Nabukuar
enslaved a large number of the Juda
Jewish people and brought them to
Babylon
as captives.
And this captivity lasted at least 50
years around 50 years around 50 years.
So the Jews had to live in Babylonia and
they wrote this great uh this this great
passage right by the rivers of Babylon.
We remember Zion or something like that.
And there's this uh pop band called Bony
M. Bony M that converted that into a pop
song by the rivers of Babylon. We
remembered Zion or something like that.
So for 50 years the Jews were in
captivity in Babylon and in other parts
of the Babylon Babylonian Empire.
Um and yeah that was a deal. So Nabu
Kudrachar was this great evil Babylonian
king who did that. Now
eventually Nabu Kudrachar was defeated
by Kurush the great Persian emperor and
Kurush def Cyrus Cyrus the great you
want to use a Greek name Cyrus the great
his name his actual name was Kurush so
Kurush defeated Namukur he took over the
Babylonian Empire he freed the Jews and
gave them permission to go back to Judea
so they go back to Judea and Judea by
this time is part of the Persian Empire
also because he has conquered all of
that. So the Jews are finally able to
return to Judea and uh they obviously
see Kurush as a great benefactor as a
great generous benevolent king and they
became influenced by the religion that
Kurush practiced which was Zaratustra's
religion a quasi inversion of the Vic
religion right that's what Zeratustra
practiced so um that's what Kurush
practiced so the Jews Judaism is
obviously a monotheistic religion it's
the original monotheist istic religion,
the original Abrahamic religion and this
became influenced by the various
elements of Zoroastrianism.
For example, Zoroastrianism is a
polytheistic religion. First of all,
today many Zoroastrians themselves
believe it's a monotheistic religion
which is a lie. Zoroastrianism has this
concept of a supreme deity called Aurora
Mazda. And there is this shadow deity,
the mirror opposite of aurora mazda.
There is Angramanu.
That's that's the evil one, right? So
you have a good versus bad duality in
Zorastrianism. But you also have other
divinities like the Yazatas. You also
have the das who are the bad guys now
and and so on. So you've got these
multiple levels of divinities in
Zoroastrianism.
The Jews, they took some of those
concepts, those polytheistic concepts,
but they converted those into
monotheistic concepts. The Yazatas,
they were these divinities, the these
gods, they were converted into the
angels of Judaism. Angels. So the angels
are not gods. They are beings with some
aspect of divinity given bestowed upon
them by the great great uh Yahweh. Yah,
right? So they took that from
Zorastanism,
the concept of these secondary gods, but
they converted those into angels. So we
only have one god. We only believe in
one god. And these angels are are beings
that god has blessed with certain extra
powers, but they're not gods. So we are
still monotheistic, but they they
borrowed that from zorostrinism.
Secondly, the concept of paradise.
So the word paradise apparently has a
Persian origin. It means a walled garden
of kind of sorts something like that. So
apparently even this concept has been
taken from Zoroastinism. I'm not I'm not
sure if Zoroastinism has this concept of
paradise. I'm not sure about that. But
they took this word paradise from the
Persian language and they they said that
you know after death uh you go to
paradise or you go to hell that sort of
thing.
So some of these concepts have been
taken from Zoroastrianism but they have
been incorporated into a monotheistic
religion Judaism. So yeah, there is
definitely a Zoroastrian influence on u
on Judaism,
right? Amisha says, "In what ways were
the Vissigotss and the Ostrogoths
different? And what was the relationship
of the Vissigotss to ancient Rome?"
Interesting question. The Vissigotss and
the Ostrogoths.
First of all, both these names, the
Vissigotss and the Ostrogoths, it has a
common term, Goths.
Who are the Goths? The Goths were a
Germanic people who originally lived in
Eastern Europe. So, let's uh go to
Google.
They essentially lived in parts of
Ukraine and Eastern Europe. So let's
Google this
uh Gothic
people
original
homeland.
Original homeland of the Gothic people
Scandinavia. They originated in
Scandinavia but they used to live in
Eastern Europe. Okay. Here we have it.
The Gothic people. This was their
homeland. As you can see they originated
somewhere in Scandinavia but they lived
in Eastern Europe. the Ukraine region
and so on. Uh yeah, so they originally
came from Scandinavia. They came down
south and eventually they lived in uh
present day Ukraine, Romania, all of
that. Okay. So they were living there in
the 3rd century AD roughly, let's say.
So the gods live in in the Ukraine
region, Eastern European region around
3rd century AD. Then you have a Hunic
invasion of Europe. Huns. Who are these
Huns? The same Hoons who were invading
India at the time.
The same Hoons they ruled Central Asia
and the step region of Europe and all
that. And they wanted their motto was we
should rule the world. If we can we
should, right? We are well organized. We
are barbaric. We can tolerate any
hardship. We should rule the world. So
they were trying to invade India and
Rome at the Rome at the same time. The
Huns.
The Houns eventually founded something
called Hungary. H U N G R Y Hungary. So
the Huns they they
uh
invaded Europe. The invasion began
around this time. So the Gothic people
who were living in Ukraine and Romania,
the eastern parts of Europe. They
they're like, "Where do we go now? The
Hoons are too barbaric, too powerful.
They will destroy us." So they started
knocking on the doors of the Roman
Empire. Please let us in. Please, we
have to we have to we have to survive.
Let's let us in. So the Romans allow the
gods to come into the Roman Empire and
settle on the banks of the Danube river,
a river named after an ancient Vic
goddess, Danube. So the gods settle down
around the along the Danub river and in
a couple of years they fight Rome and
defeat Rome in Adrianople
in Turkey.
So they fight Rome. They defeat Rome
major defeat in Adrian Adrianopople.
But eventually they kind of become
allies and enemies of the Romans. At the
same time, lot of Gothic soldiers served
in the Roman armies. Sometimes the Goths
fought the Romans in uh the fifth
century. The Goths sacked Rome which was
a traumatic event for Rome. I think 410
AD or something. Allaric the first was
the Gothic king who sacked Rome.
Um so these gods who sacked Rome,
they are called the Vissigoths, the
western gods because they eventually
went westwards and they founded a
kingdom in what the Romans called Iberia
which is now called Spain,
Vigoththic Iberia.
They founded a Gothic kingdom in Iberia
in Spain. And they they ruled until the
Arabic invasion of Iberia.
Okay. And the Arabs ruled Iberia, Spain
for a few centuries. And eventually the
gods were able to defeat them in the
Reconista.
So the Spanish are the descendants of
the Ostrogoths. Oh, sorry, the
Vissigots, the Visigots. The Western
gods. So the gods eventually split into
two two branches. The western gods and
the eastern gods. The western gods are
the visigots. The eastern gods are the
Ostrogoths. The eastern gods, they
founded a kingdom in Italy.
Yeah. So the the eastern gods had a
kingdom in Italy and the western gods
had a kingdom in Spain and the
descendants of of those people are the
Spaniards of today. Of course it's more
complicated than that but kind of kind
of right. So that's the difference
between the e the eastern and the
western gods. The eastern are the ostro
gods and the western are the wissy gods.
And that's the relationship with Rome as
well.
Right. Udit Mahesh says, "If the British
were reluctant to settler colonize India
because of its hot and humid climate,
then how come they displaced the
Aborigines in Australia and settler
colonized it even though Australia is a
very hot and humid place with only
summer and typhoons all throughout the
year?" Okay, good question. Very
interesting question. Let's once again
go to Google.
Okay, Australia climate.
Australia
climate zones. Let's see Australia's
climate zones.
You'll find something very interesting
here.
These are the different climate zones of
Australia. Okay.
Climate classification
of Australia. Let's let's um
give me a second. I'll I'll I'll enlarge
this if possible.
Yeah, it's not going to work. One
second. Australian climate zones,
Australian.
Okay, let's just go to the Wikipedia
article. Perhaps that'll be I suppose
easier. Give me a second. I'll open
Wikipedia for this. As always, let me
remind you Wikipedia is not necessarily
a great source of information, but for
the sake of u saving time. Let's look at
this. So, if you look at this image of
Australia, you will see that temperate
climate,
okay, the green parts.
Okay, one second. Even this is not a
great uh way of looking at it.
So, essentially,
one second. Give me a second. I'll come
back here.
Okay. Once again, we come here. This is
a better representation. All right. So
if you look at the coastal the regions
the coastal regions of Australia the
green zones okay the green zones and the
blue zones you will find these are the
pleasant places to live in if you live
in let's say Perth if you live in
Adelaide if you live in Melbourne you
are essentially living in the
Mediterranean region or you have the
same climate as you have in California
which essentially could be considered to
be the nicest climate in the world
neither too hot neither too cold very
pleasant, pretty cool
and that sort of thing. So, and if you
now if you look at the Australian
population population density, okay,
let's do that
population density.
Well, you will see that the majority of
the population is once again distributed
in those regions only
where you have the nicest climate.
So, there are part Okay, this is the
best one. Look at this.
So there are parts of Australia where
you have the nicest climate which is
where the British settled. In the rest
of Australia which is dry arid with bad
climate the a the aboriginals people
were allowed to live there but under
British control.
So there are parts of Australia, the the
southern portion of Australia, the Perth
region that has beautiful climate, the
kind of climate the British love,
California kind of climate. Uh Sicily
kind of climate
um K daz in France, Mari, that kind of
climate that's the best climate in the
world and that's where the British
settled and they did not settle anywhere
else. I mean of course now you have
populations in Darwin and Kairens and
we're not where you have the the same
climate as Chennai for example but yeah
eventually since they have taken over
the country the continent they settled
in other places also but the majority of
the population is in those nice climate
regions so that kind of explains how
things went.
Okay. Atul Narwan says when we talk
about Indian history then excuse me
excuse me when we talk about history
then why do people not take into account
the fact that India has been under
foreign occupation for a thousand years
they doubt their ancestors all the time
and somehow believe that anything of
value can only come from the west how to
erase this doubt from the Indian mind
how to tell them that anc their
ancestors have done a complete comp
comparatively comparatively great job by
not letting Bat become fully Abrahamic
or fully colonized.
Okay. So why do Indians not take into
account the fact that India was under
foreign occupation for a thousand years?
Let me tell you why.
Go back to the time where where you went
in school or college. You had history
textbooks. What did they say your
history textbooks about the
British occupation? Did they call it
foreign occupation?
Did they call it foreign? Did you ever
see the word foreign occupation
anywhere? Did you see the term
occupation anywhere? No, they call it
the colonial period or something. It
sounds so nice
like almost like a good thing. the
colonial period. When they write about
the Muggal Empire, they'll say the great
Muggal dynasty,
right? Babar the Great, Humayun the the
unfortunate, Akbar the Great, Orurange
is slightly not so good. But even
Orangab had some great qualities. I'm
sure that sort of thing. They don't put
your history textbooks don't portray
this as a foreign occupation. They treat
the Mongols as Indians.
They even treat the British as bene
benevolent benefactors. Lord William
Bentik, such a great man who did so many
wonderful reforms in our miserably
backward Indian society. That's what
they tell you.
You are indoctrinated indoctrinated. You
are brainwashed into believing that the
1,000 years of foreign occupation was a
great time for India of great social
reform and progress because we were so
backward and barbaric. We needed these
foreigners to come and
pull us out of our backwardness and we
are still backward because we are still
Hindus.
It is not the fault of Indians that they
are mentally colonized and they suffer
from an inferiority complex. is
engineered into the education system.
All your great leaders, most of them
believe this.
Most of your great political leaders
believe all this nonsense. Most of your
school teachers, university professors
believe this. They grew up learning
this. They they they believe that India
needs to be pulled out of its
backwardness. They believe that the
foreign occupation was the best time for
India when all these regressive
practices where the foreigners tried to
so generously and beneely remove from
India.
It all depends on the lens that you use
to see the foreign occupation. So first
of all they will not use the term
foreign occupation
because once you use the term foreign
occupation you see images of Nazi
Germany coloniz occupying France and
whatnot Europe.
So if you use the term for an occupation
it immediately has negative
connotations. So you use the term
colonial period muggle empire and so on.
So they use see words can be really
powerful and once that goes into your
mind as a child colonial period ah the
colonial period what a great great time
it was chi now look at the look at look
at India today the colonial period all
those great buildings they built for us
all those great railways they built for
us. Ah,
so much good the British did for us.
The textbooks won't teach teach you
about the the the barbaric famines that
they engineered, about the atrocities in
1857 after 1857, the hundreds of
millions of Indians who were starved to
death, the all the brutal tortures they
did to India, the British only, they
will not talk about what the Turks did
to India. So because of very selective
facts that are presented and
misrepresented in your textbooks, you
all grow up believing that this was the
best period of Indian history
that our culture is the most backward
culture in the world, right? And it
still exists which is which is an
abomination.
So until we change the education system,
this is going to continue.
But why is it not being changed? Well,
ask your leadership.
Ask your leaders.
Right.
A feminist slayer says, "What was the
long-term impact of the Huna invasions
on India's political and cultural
landscape?"
India's political cultural landscape.
Huna invasions. The Hoons. The Hoons who
set the Ostrots and Visigots running
from from Romania and Ukraine into Roman
into Roman territory. The same horns who
invaded the Roman Empire at the same
time they were invading India. The same
horns. So we called them the schwa
hunas, the white horns for whatever
reason. Maybe they were had white flags
or white dresses or I don't know
whatever white skin I don't think so
whatever. So we called them the white
horns the hunas. And uh the Gupta empire
resisted the white hoons and defeated
them multiple times. Our last great
Gupta emperor Scandanda Gupta spent his
entire life and career fighting the Huns
and repulsing wave after wave of Hunik
invasion. But eventually the Huns made
ingress into India. They started with
Gandhar. Uh the first Hunik king of
Gandhar was what? Torana. Tora Mana.
Very naughty guy. He destroyed
Takshashira. That idiot. That absolute
idiot destroyed Takshashira.
Yeah, I I don't think he realized what a
stupid mistake he did. Toramana probably
is the guy who also built the Bameyian
Buddhas. Is it? Let's Let's Google it.
I'm not sure who built the Bameanian
Buddhas. Who constructed the Bamean
Buddhas?
Bame. Who? Buddhas. Okay. Buddhist monks
during the Heptilite principalities.
Yes. The Heptilites are the are the Shwa
Hunas.
So, which was the king? Which was the
king?
Who who was the king? Was it Toramana?
Let me see.
It doesn't say Torana here. So, it's not
sure which Heptilite king, which Hunik
king built the Bamian Buddhas. It could
possibly be Toramana.
So, maybe Torana regretted what he did
and that's why he constructed the great
Buddhas in Bameyan or whatever. But he's
the idiot Toana who destroyed
Takshashila in western India presently
temporarily part of Pakistan. So, that
was a disaster for India. Yeah, the
Hunas were the the Hoons were well less
civilized people. They were nomads
and they did not understand the the
value of civilization until they settled
in India. So initially they would have
said let's destroy everything. So he
destroyed Takshashila that idiot Tramana
and eventually most likely he's the guy
who built the Bameyian Buddhas in a
later time. Maybe he may have repented
of what he did. So he said let me
contribute something to culture and
civilization eventually and and Tora had
a son.
If you think toana was bad at least he
tried to do something good later. His
son was Mihir Koul.
Mahihir Khul was hated universally by
everyone. He was hated by the Buddha by
the Buddhists by the Hindus by the
Brahinss by the atheists by the Indians
by everybody. He was an absolute
barbarian. Mhirkul
he was an atheist. He said I will
destroy all religious all all whatever
religion exists all religious
manifestations
and uh he he called himself Rajar
Raja or something the king of kings
Maharaj he called himself Mhirkul and
the king of kings eventually he was
defeated by some other king and he
became a vasal then he did not call
himself Maharaj just call him called
himself Raja he became a vasal so
Mihirkul was was one of the nasty hunik
kings
and he caused a lot of pain during the
time he ruled. Eventually you have later
hunic kings who did a lot of good
things. You have the um
you have the Hindu Shahi empire uh the
Hindu Shahi kingdom in Gandhar which is
who who is who are the Hindu Shahis?
There were the huns, hunik kings who
ruled India, who ruled northwest India,
the Gandhar Kashmir region. And they
fought the Turks.
They defended India from the Turks. The
same Huns, the Hindu Shahis. Sorry, no,
no, no, not the Hindu shah. The Turk
Shahis. You first have the Turk Shahis
who are the Hind who are the descendants
of the Huns who ruled in Gandhar and
Kashmir. Turk Shahis. Then you have the
Hindu Shahis who may or may not have
been Turks or maybe who may or may not
have been HS or maybe mixed or whatever.
So yeah, you have the Turk Shahis who
were Hindus and who defended India from
other barbaric Turks.
So overall the Hunas they did cause
destruction in India. The worst thing
they did was destroy Takashila.
They also did a lot of good things for
India. Eventually once they became
Indian after a couple of generations uh
they built the Buddhas in Bameyan they
they did a lot of religious work one of
the hunik kings was the patron of
brahagupta for example if you look at
let's go in wiki go to wikipedia okay if
you see this
brahagupta one of our great uh
great mathematicians
so if you look at this you will see that
his patron
was a king who could have been
a second generation Huna.
Okay, I'm not sure where it is but I'm
sure you will find it. So that's the
deal.
So eventually the Hoons did contribute
good things to India. Initially they
were barbarians and India eventually
civilized them after a couple of
generations.
Um yeah that was the deal about the
huns.
Shouha says during the time of the
saraspati hindu civilization that period
of our history uh our ancestors built
from that time they built an extremely
good drainage system which is even
better than today's drainage systems in
most Indian cities in all Indian cities.
Do you think this this is because at
that time India's monsoon was way
heavier and it is human nature to adapt
to these extreme climates. Okay. So our
ancestors from that time period, they
built these extremely efficient drainage
systems.
For example, a few years ago when there
was this massive flooding in Pakistan,
most of the cities in Pakistan had these
big floods that lasted for days. But in
Mohenador, Harapa, the water drained out
because of the 5,000 year old drainage
system that still functioned.
Imagine that. So that's how good these
drainage systems were which our
ancestors built. Why were they so good?
Is it because we had a much heavier
rainy season at the time much heavier
monsoon so we had to adapt to those to
that climate and that's why we built
better rainy system. Is it the case? Is
it the case?
But
is it really the case?
The fact is that everything from that
time was better than today.
All this see that time period was a
fully urbanized time period of our
civilization.
India was fully urbanized. It was a
fully urbanized society at the time.
Even small towns were laid out in grid
structures. Even villages were laid out
in grid structures. And the metropolitan
metropolitan cities like Harrapa,
Mahindadar, Rakari, Birana or whatnot or
Kalimangan. These were all laid out in
the grid structure that you see in
western cities today,
right? So you had beautiful town
planning
and you had multi-story buildings 5 6
thousand years ago
and you had ports and dockyards and
harbors with hydrogenering that that
rivals what we have today. If you look
at the the dockyard the harbor at Lothal
and Dul Vira. Those two harbors if you
look at those
they compare favorably in size and
capability in capacity
compared to the port of Vishaka Patnam
where you can have which can
accommodated aircraft carriers today
that's how advanced the engineering was.
So it's not like only the drainage
systems were better than today's India.
Everything was better than today's
India.
What does it indicate, my dear viewers?
It indicates, my dear viewers, that your
ancestors 5,000 years ago had much
higher standards than you all have
today.
Facts. Face it.
Nirvana Shanks says, "Mongol Empire,
huge, massive, yet messages went fast.
How did they do it?" And then there's a
question about music. So, two questions.
Mongol Empire, huge, massive, massive.
Would you like to see the size of the
Mongol Empire? It they had conquered
half the world. Okay. Mongol Empire,
full extent.
Full extent. Come on, let's have it.
Okay. Here's the full extent of the
Mongol Empire. Check it out.
It's like they deliberately chose to not
invade only one part of Asia. Right.
Right. They deliberately chose to not
invade only one part of Asia. They took
everything else and they went all the
way into Eastern Europe. So this is the
size of the Mongol Empire at its peak.
And so it's it's clearly a massive
empire. It's it's like half the entire
known world of the time. more than half.
And yet they were able to coordinate
things across the empire. Messages went
fast. How? The Mongols were nomads
originally and to even today they're
nomads.
They were used to great hardships
and they had brilliant strategists
such as Subotaai the great general the
greatest general in history who could
coordinate military deployments over
hundreds of kilometers in real time
which means that they had messages going
and coming at lightning speed. I have
10,000 soldiers. A tum a tuman a tuman
is 10,000 soldiers. I am controlling my
tuman here. 10,000 200 km away. I have
my other tuman over there and I have
instructed them to do certain things and
we will meet together and crush our
enemy from two sides in a way that the
enemy can't even imagine. For that I
need coordination in real time with my
10,000 guys 200 km away as we are
approaching the enemy from two sides.
How do you do that without telephones
and whatnot? That's the question. And
that's just a military maneuver. We're
talking about an empire that's like
10,000 kilometers wide. How do you
control the entire empire and know
exactly what's happening in various
parts of the empire? Because of their uh
their postal system which was based on
riders, horse riders. So they had these
postal not really postal system but
message relay system. They had these
relay posts all over the empire where
you would have fresh horses waiting for
you. So if I am a messenger of the great
emperor Shri Chingis Khan and I have
this this letter with his stamp
then all I have to do is I I I take a
horse a fresh horse and I ride as fast
as possible in one day 70 80 kilometers
over one p over the period of one day I
reach the next check post check post I'm
exhausted my horse is exhausted I give
my horse to these guys they will take
care of the horse and in 2 three days
the horse will recover I'll take a fresh
horse I'll sleep for a few hours and
I'll get going
Or maybe I will just hand it over like a
relay race, a 4x100 m relay race. I'll
hand over the message to the guy who's
waiting for me there. And I go to sleep
and he starts the journey in the night
and he goes to the next checkpoint which
a checkpoint post which is another 70 80
km away. So that way you can have
messages travel several thousand
kilometers in just a few days and that's
enough in those days to be able to to
control the empire. So that's how it was
done there. at these radiating networks
that went out in all directions across
the empire where you could have messages
travel incredibly fast
compared to the way messages traveled in
those days. So that's how they were able
to do it. Now about your uh the question
would Axel Rose or Robert Plant be able
to sing those tremendous ragas I was
talking about in yesterday's liveream
provided they have such a broad vocal
range of course they can of course they
can any competent singer and Axel Rose
and Robert Plant are some of the best
singers that we have any singer of that
of that caliber can sing raas they will
obviously need to be taught the
fundamentals of raas what a raa is right
what the notes are ascending scale
descending scale uh Consent consonant
note the drone notes the puckard and so
on right once you so a little bit of
practice they'll be able to sing raas no
question about it no question about it
right
geopolitical dub says what events were
taking place outside of bhat or in other
contemporary civilizations if any
existed during the period of the
dasharajan yuda the battle the war of
the 10 kings the oldest recorded
geopolitical
event kind of a world war for the time
right. Um so first of all to answer the
question you have to kind of place this
event in the chronology of history.
Only then can we talk about what was
happening outside of India outside of
Bhat if we know roughly in what time
period this war happened. The the war of
the 10 kings. So the war of the 10 kings
is is is recorded in the riga
right and it's a pivotal event in in the
history of our civilization. It is uh
king sudas the the son of king dodas who
was up against a confederation of 10
clans
and diwadas was an expansionist. He
starts from northern central India moves
westwards westwards towards the sap
sapasindu region and the kings of the
region they say that this is a big
threat to us. They they ally together
they create create a confederation of
more than 10 kings to fight together
against the vodas
sudas and sudas still defeats them all
with the help of Lord Indra.
So that and and then those 10 kings and
their clans are sent into exile out of
India forever.
And that probably is the event that
sparked off the the expansion the
geographical expansion of the
Indo-Uropean language family. So that is
a pivotal event in world history. The
first ever war that's recorded in human
history, the oldest geopolitical
conflict that we know of. And
it it laid the foundation of of Indian
civilization because after the the
victory the Dvodas had to reassure
everybody else in India that okay I'm
now the guy. I'm going to rule you all
but I am not going to be an oppressor.
You're all welcome. Everyone's welcome.
Your gods are welcome. When we do yagna
everybody's god is welcome. We will give
offerings in the yagna. Not just to
Indra in mitra veruna through agni. We
will give offerings to everybody's gods.
So that was a essentially a message of
peace, a message of inclusion that all
people who live in the subcontinent are
now part of our civilization. Pivotal
event in our civilizational history. Now
the question is when did this happen?
Only then we can decide what was
happening outside.
If it's mentioned in the rigida, it
happened before the rigida was written
kind of the pre-vedic age. Now the
question is when was the rigida written?
That's the question. The only way to to
date the rigida is not to listen to rula
tapper or Michael widzel or or or
whoever else
maxer 1500 BC arians came to India
invaders and 1200 BC they wrote the
rigida utter idiocy right
let's we you have to examine this a
priority from first principles what
clues do we have in the text itself that
could kind of help us understand when it
was written.
The the clearest clues are in the one
divinity that is referenced over and
over and over and over again. Of course,
Indra is the one great divinity that is
referred to a lot of times. You have
Rudra also Lord Shiva but another
divinity is Saraswati
and Saraswati is extolled but not as a
goddess kind of as a goddess as a
divinity but also as a physical river.
The Saraswati is referred referenced so
many times in the Rigveda and the Rigida
speaks about the Saraswati in these
glowing terms in this kind of aruck
terms. It's an awe inspiring river. It's
a loudly roaring river. It is the mother
of floods.
So clearly it's referring to a a river
that is in her prime. And the Saraswati
we know dried out in the in the second
half of its course around 1500 BC.
The Saraspati it used to be fed uh by by
glacial melt snow melt in the Himalayas
and the Indian monsoon was very heavy at
the time. That's why the Sarasati was
gigantic river which flowed into the
western Indian Ocean. But eventually the
Indian motions monsoon started declining
around 6,000 BC and the Saraswati
started also declining and by 1500 BC
the Saraspati has dried out in the in
the in the lower half of its course and
it died out and created this big
gigantic lake for a while and the lake
eventually dried out and became the Thar
desert.
So all of this is around 1500 BC. So
clearly the rigid has written closer to
6,000 BC than to 1500 BC. So let's
assume for the sake of this discussion
the rigida was written in 6,000 BC. What
was happening in the rest of the world
at the time?
People were living in caves. People were
wearing animal skins outside of India.
People were eating raw meat outside of
India.
That's all we know.
That is all we know what events were
taking place. People were hunting
animals.
People were eating raw meat. People were
living in caves. People were re wearing
animal skins that's all we know
right Krishna Raunat of the Surinami
Netherlands says does there exist a
concept like sin in the four dharmic
religions Hinduism Jinism Buddhism
Sikhism of course it's called pop
it's called pop sin is pap uh so that's
an equivalent term in the Sanskrit
language in the dharmic world pop But
it's different from the Abrahamic sin.
In the Abrahamic religions, sin
will ensure damnation.
In Christianity, you can sin, but as
long as you confess, as long as you are
shriven,
you will be absolved and you'll be fine.
So all you have to do is to do nasty
stuff. But then you go and and and and
repent and you go to a priest and you
confess all your say sins and the priest
will give you absolution and you may
have to do repentance of some kind. The
priest will tell you exactly how to
repent. And then as long as you do the
repentance properly, you will be
absolved of your sins and you will go to
paradise heaven. And if you do sins and
you don't repent and you don't confess
and you don't absolve yourself, have
yourself absolved and you don't do the
necessary repentance or whatever, you
will go to hell where you where you will
be tortured for all eternity in fair.
Yes. By eliabolo.
So that's the deal in the Abrahamic
religions in Christianity. In Islam it's
very similar I suppose. I'm not sure. In
Islam they have a day of judgment uh
cayamat or something. In Judaism also
they have uh hell I suppose heaven and
hell.
Uh so in the Abrahamic religions sin is
tied it's connected to the concept of
heaven and hell. If you are a sinner you
will be sentenced to eternal damnation
in hell. The torments of hell for all
eternity. That's what you will suffer.
In the dharmic religions, sin is
connected to the concept of karma.
So you can be a sinner. If you have
sinned, it's going to be acred to your
karma, your karmic balance. And that
will determine the kind of
uh not afterlife but rebirth you have.
So that is a different kind of concept
compared to what you have in the Abraic
religions. In in in the Dharmic
religions, we have the concept of
rebirth, reincarnation, cycles of
reincarnation. People can be
reincarnated hundreds of times. And so
most mostly you don't have any memories
of your past lives, but some great
people do. Apparently, I'm not one of
those. I have no memories of my past
lives. So,
so the question arises that why why is
why is the world unequal? Why are some
people just born into prosperity, born
into um you know into into a family that
is prosperous, that is that is wealthy?
Why are you born into wealth? Why are
some people just born stronger with
better abilities with better intellect
than other people? Because they did some
good things in their past lives which is
what gave them gave them these
attributes. So this is the this is the
fruit of the good deeds that you did in
your past lives. And why are some people
just you know born with other attributes
that are not so good because of bad
things they did in the in their past
lives that sort of thing. So what you do
in life echoes in eternity through
eternity via the process of of rebirth
and and the karmic uh consequences of
what you've done. So you do have the
concept of sin in the dharmic religions.
Anything that that is hurtful, that is
harmful to other people, to yourself, to
society is sinful and that's going to
give you bad karma and that's going to
have consequences. So that's the
difference between the dharmic and abra
abrahabic concepts of sin.
Okay. Um, Yajjnalia says, "If you search
on Google Scholar, occupational
endogami, quotes included, most of the
references don't seem to be talking
about India. Don't you think that's
interesting?" Well, that's very
interesting. Let's take Let's check it
out. So, let's go to Google Scholar.
Google Scholar. We go there and we put
into quotes
occupational
Indo
Indogami
and what do we get assortative mating by
cultural and economic occupational
status which is not about India it's
Chicago marital selection occupational
straight up once again not India
occupational status and marriage
selection
is there anything about India here
nothing
very interesting occupation quite high
occupational endogamy can neverless
nevertheless be found in English context
and so on and so forth so it's clear
from what we see here we have Kilmer
Irisher which seems to be Scotland and
the collers and their wives which is
okay count Durham which is in Yorkshire
northern
England. What else do we have? What else
do we have? English rural societies,
spinners and weavers of of a United
States mi
intersecting world. Liverpool's merchant
community
uh pang of manipur that's India. Okay.
Uh occupational blah blah blah blah.
Three-way interaction effects.
That's a book review. You have something
in Korea.
H the cast system of India occupational
endogamy.
So there there's mysore here. So it's
it's Catalonia you have. So as you can
see occupational endogamy
most of these papers they don't refer to
India. There's Catalonia, there's
Scotland, there's England, there's
United States, there's what not. So
occupational endogamy seems to be
something that's prevalent the world
over.
But if it happens in India, it is cast
system. It is evil. You see how they
have selectively
singled out India
for demonization.
If there's Indogami in India, it is the
evil cast system. If it is elsewhere, it
is occupational Indogamy. It is
perfectly natural. In any advanced
society, you have stratification of
society. You see, but if it happens in
India, it is evil cast system. You
Indian Hindus are so evil.
So you see this selective
cherry-picking.
You have to understand how these
narratives have been crafted over time
and then they are taught to you and you
grow up believing these things that your
culture is evil.
Yeah. So very interesting. I'm so glad
that Yajnulkia has pointed this out. I
think you know someone should write a
paper on this, a proper research paper
on this. very interesting meta research
research about all this research that's
been done statistical sampling
statistical analysis the top 500 search
results that you get in Google Scholar
what's the percentage that's about India
and what's the context and stuff very
interesting
uh so thank you sir for for pointing
this out um okay
Aayush Singh says please tell us about
the deeds of Rotten Tata you once said
it was too early to talk about him I
once said probably a few months ago
It was too too early to talk about
Ratant Tata. Yeah, I I I'm sure I said
that. Let me put this in the right
context. Are you? And everybody else.
You see the French Revolution,
it happened in the late 18th century,
1789 to 1799,
right? 1789 to 1799, 10 years roughly
French Revolution happened. The Chinese
foreign minister Shiaoin Lai,
he was asked by an American delegation
in 1972,
what
what do you think of the consequences of
the French Revolution?
Of the effects of the that the French
Revolution had
he was asked this in 1972. He said it is
too early to talk about it.
It's too early. It's too early to say.
Kind of like that.
All right. Okay. Let's take one more
question. Excuse me. Uh Ashish Ashes
says, "Since you don't have any science
episodes, I would I have a quick
question." Okay, this is a question
about physics. Okay, let's turn it into
a historical question, shall we? I am
I'm a genius. I can turn physics
questions into history questions. And
are you wondering how? Oh, let me show
you how. First, let's read the question.
In the interstellar movie, there was a
principle that time moves slowly near
the high gravity zones such as black
holes. Okay. TK. Therefore, from our
perspective, the age of the universe is
13 billion years. But from the
perspective of black holes or primordial
black holes or whatever, the age of the
universe would be way less than 13 13
billion years, perhaps a few million
years. And could it be true that the
singularity at the singularity
perspective, the birth and death of the
universe is happening simultaneously?
So how do I convert this into a history
question? Well, this is a question about
the history of the universe, right? So
we'll convert this, we'll see this from
the perspective of history.
So there is something called
gravitational time dilation
and there is something that you will
find in my books that I'm writing a book
right now. I'm I'm period serializing it
and you will find the links in the
description. Sure. So what is
gravitational time dilation? It means
that the closer you are to a massive
object, the slower time passes. The
universe, its fabric is made up of four
dimensions. The three spatial dimensions
and the fourth dimension is time. So the
universe is made up of a fourdimensional
fabric of spacetime. And the presence of
mass curves spacetime. It curves not
just space but also time. Even time is
curved. Do you know why everything is
mass? Why do why do things fall? Because
of gravity. Gravity is simply the
manifestation of the curvature of
spaceime.
Okay? And the weight that we have. Let's
say your weight is 70 kilos. You know
why you have a weight of 70 kilos? It's
because of the curvature of time.
More curvature of time, less curvature
of space. The curvature of time is
causing what you consider to be your
weight. Your head
is older than your feet. Do you know
that?
by a very small fraction of time. But
your head is older than your feet. Your
feet are younger because they are closer
to the center of the planet than your
head.
So the closer you are to a mass, the
slower time passes.
And this effect becomes extreme near
very massive objects such as black
holes. If you are close to the event
horizon of a black hole of a massive
black hole, time passes really slowly
for you. But from your perspective at
the near the black hole you feel that
time is passing just fine. My watch is
ticking just the way it is. But if you
have a friend who is observing you from
a very large distance away they will see
you as totally frozen. You're not moving
at all because for for them time is
passing passing passing at a different
speed. So the closer you are to a black
hole, the slower time passes for you.
Which means that the external universe
seems to seems to be moving much faster.
Which means that if you actually go
inside a black hole, if you cross the
event horizon, you will see things that
are so weird looking outwards. In the
time that it takes your heart to beat
once, you will see the birth and death
of stars.
That's what you see if you're taking
that final journey
towards the singularity. So from the
perspective of somebody who's near a
black hole, let's say you have a black
hole that was created right after the
birth of the universe and if if you had
a person an observer there near the
event horizon for them the universe may
have lived for just a few years
for a few centuries but for us it is
13.8 billion years. So yes, it all
depends on where you are and how close
you are to a massive object. If you are
in the vicinity very close to the event
horizon of a black hole, time passes at
a different speed for you and the
universe seems to be playing out in in
fast forward, right? And from a
singularity's perspective, yeah, well,
it's not really a a physics question
anymore. It's a it's a philosophical
question because it can't really you
can't really do that experiment. But
from a singularity's perspective, the
birth and the death of the universe
happen simultaneously.
Yeah, this is the weirdness of general
relativity. That's how weird physics can
be and that's how fascinating physics
is. Okay, that's the end of the
questions for today. I have more
questions, but I am I'm running out of
time. I should take some questions from
the from the live chat as well.
All right, I have no idea what this
pugloo means, but all right.
Yes, Aayosh, it is it is still too
early.
It's still too early to talk about it. I
can see that people have taken super
chats. I'm going to have to finish these
because Yeah. Okay, I'll I'll finish the
super super chats. Uh Data
Ganesh, thank you ma'am. Thank you so
much for being a member. Thank you so
much. I really appreciate that. Thank
you. Ram says Kalikat Zamuran kings
allowed Muslims to settle in Malabar
with just one condition of not killing
cows as noted by even
later Malabar voted for partition. Can
these events be invoked to determine
future policies? Everything has a cause
and effect chain and what happens in the
what happened in the past can be used as
a model to kind of
predict predict what could happen in the
future.
So based on the things that have
happened in the past, based on the
cyclicality of nature of of of history
and and
of um of human nature, you can kind of
say that if things happen in the past,
they could similar things could happen.
The same pattern could recur in the
future.
So yes, these events can be invoked
to determine what could happen in the
future and to determine appropriate
policies in case you want to have
something else happen. Rede indeed. Abua
Singh says, "Please make someone a mod
here when you're busy answering
questions. Some lechers disturb the
chat. Some are right here, right? Some
are here right now as well. Well, I
shall inform my moderator very strictly
that please don't fall asleep at the
wheel and do remove the lechas who may
be disturbing
um the the the other viewers. So I
apologize for that and I'll ensure I
will ensure that there is stricter
moderation going forward. Uh go says why
is India pleading now to the US to allow
it to buy Iranian oil instead of Russian
oil? Why show weakness? Now this is not
a historical question sir. Today we are
dealing with history.
I just don't understand why people have
to do this. It's a history. Look at the
title of this this episode of this
video. It says Indian and world history.
This is this is something I've seen in
Indians. Indians just want to cut
corners and and bend the rules. Right.
Anyway, since you've asked the question,
I'll say India is not pleading. India is
giving an example to the US that you
have already stopped us from buying
Iranian oil and we we went along with
your with your nonsense. Now you want us
to stop Russian oil also. Eventually you
will want us to stop everything. That's
not how it works. So if you really want
us to stop buying Russian oil, we will
buy Iran and oil. Will will you be okay
with that? There's a no. So we saying
then you you can go take a hike. India
is not pleading with anybody else. India
is not pleading. Please understand that.
Wooden armor says we have seen evidence
of Hinduism all the way to Mesopotamia.
Is there any relationship between
Hindus, Indas and Norse civilizations?
Norse civilization. There was no Norse
civilization. There was Norse culture.
If you look at their gods, these are
manifestations of ancient Indian gods.
Who is Thor? Thor is the god of the
thunderbolt and the hammer.
What is the meaning of the word vajger?
Vajger is a hammer that's made out of
the of the uh rib cage of rishi is it or
whoever it is. It's a hammer. It's also
a thunderbolt.
Lord Indra is the original Thor.
The Greeks copied Lord Indra and turned
him into Zeus. Zeus is a god with a
Vajgerra with a thunderbolt
also a hammer god. So is Jupiter and
eventually so is uh Thor. So yeah, there
is a connection. No question about it.
No question.
Prattana says as per
proper hard evidence chariot antenna
held swords only spread to Europe around
1500 BC time coinciding with Mitani
related migrations in ADNA. Our people
are finding Indas and Alalak ancestry in
Idonia.
Okay, that's interesting. If you could
give a specific reference of a paper in
the in the in the comments later on, I
could look into it. there are so many
papers and and the past two three years
I've not really
kept a breast of what's happening in the
research. Uh I was deep into the RN
inversion migration debunking thing in
2017 2018 all the way up to 2020 21 then
I kind of pulled out of it because uh
you know because
the new evidence comes in at a very slow
rate. I wanted to synthesize all the
evidence that existed until that point
and to demonstrate that this entire
story this narrative that there was an
invasion of India by arians it is a lie
and I put out a an article which brought
all the evidence together and I showed
the patterns that it's entirely a lie.
So, so then they converted that into a
migration thing from invasion to
migration and eventually they'll do all
the so all these little piece pieces of
evidence which come in they all tie in
with all the other evidence and they and
they patch up all the all the holes. So
it's like a gigantic jigsaw puzzle and
the the the the the researchers and and
the and and the narrative pro the
propagandists who are pushing the Arian
migration invasion narrative they will
selectively pick cherrypick some parts
of the evidence and misconstrue it to to
claim that there was a migration or
invasion like Michael Vitzell and his
inversion of the of the Bodhi Nasha
Sutra's the meaning of what what was
written there of an invasion to the east
instead of west that sort of thing. So
chariot antenna and hilt swords spread
to Europe around 1500 BC which is when
you have the the the the
recorded presence of Indians in Anatolia
and Syria the mitani empire right mitani
related migrations very interesting yes
and uh or people are finding industalak
ancestry in alonia the more the research
the more research happens the more
you're going to find evidence that there
were invasions not invasions there were
migrations
West of India outside of India. India
was the origin of these of these
migrations. India was the big gigantic
population center compared to the rest
of Eurasia.
And these migrations were happening out
of India. The same time that you have
the first presence of Indian cattle and
Indian people in Anatolia, in Syria and
in Egypt, at the same time you have the
first presence of Indians in Australia.
Indians were adventurers. Indians who
used to go by sea, Indians used to go
travel by land, Indians wanted to go
everywhere and and travel the world.
It's Indians who spread the Indo-Uropean
cultures everywhere. And eventually the
evidence is going going to become so
overwhelming
that it's going to be indisputable. But
these beliefs change only with the
passing of people.
You see for example
for the longest time it was believed
that black holes are nonsense.
Arthur Edington and Albert Einstein
himself were a huge opponents
of the concept of black holes. Einstein
wrote papers trying to prove that black
holes could never exist. Edington
humiliated Subramanyam Chandra Shikhar
because Chandra Shikha's research was
showing that black holes would form.
It was only after the death of Edington
and Einstein that the research in black
holes really took off.
So you will need the passage of time and
the passage of these evil propagandists
for things to change. It'll take time
but it's all going to come out
and I will be vindicated.
Pratana says pashons and kyis turks have
R1A branch shar with Kushans and
Santashta. It turns out Tari mummies are
R1B and R1A takes over in around iron
age. Very interesting. Looks like
there's been new research. I'll have to
look it look it up. I'll have to check
it out. So, tar mummies are R1B. Well,
what I had seen was that the majority
was R1A, but maybe there's new research
and new samples have come out. I'm not
sure. I'll have to check it out. Pashons
and Kygis Turks have R1A branch shared
with Kushans and Shinta.
Tari mummies are R1B. So are you saying
the tarim mummies are not connected to
the Kushans? Very interesting. I love to
check out this new research. Like I
said, I've not been keeping in touch
with the research the past 3 four years,
but I'll check it out. So, thank you for
pointing this out, sir. Thank you very
much. Harshai says, why is
cousin why cousin marriage is common in
idli state?
It was done in Mahabha too. I have no
idea what idli states are.
What is Mahabha? Mahabharat. Did you
have cousin marriages in Mahabharat? I'm
not sure about this sir. Not sure.
Sorry.
Ash Ketchum says, "How did the British
establish corruption in India?" They
institutionalized corruption. Example,
the British created something called the
judiciary. The judiciary's role was to
uh end dispute to to resolve and mediate
in disputes and to enforce the um
enforce contracts and the the objective
was to ensure that the British got their
things done very fast. But if you are
creating a judiciary even the Indians
will have to because they are ruled by
you they will also approach the
judiciary for various disputes. So the
British ensured they they implemented a
two-t tire system that when there is a
British person who comes to the
judiciary with a case the case is
disposed of fast lightning fast. But
when an Indian person has will approach
the judiciary
that will be delayed. Those cases will
be delayed. They will be asked for
bribes. the the papers will be will will
get stuck in various files
and each stage of the way you to go and
approach that clerk and pay some bribe.
So this was another means of the another
way of demoralizing the Indians and and
and and and you know oppressing them.
Isn't this called corruption? That's one
way to institutionalize corruption in
India. Prattana says Italy, Spain,
Greece have low 10 to 20% yamna industry
only. Does it mean separate origins or
two or even three sources and regions of
origin? So the Yamna invasion happened
about 4 and a half thousand years ago.
It came from the east and it spread into
Europe and in a very short period of
time historically speaking. The Yamna
conquered most of Europe and they
conducted a proper genocide of the
European males and then they interbred
intermingled with the women folk who
they did not kill and their descendants
are today's Europeans. Now the extent of
the genocide would differ in various
parts of Europe. In many parts of Europe
almost all the males were killed off.
For example, if you go to the British
islands, uh the people who built
Stonehenge,
their male folk were killed off
entirely. Their women were not killed.
And today's English British people, the
Celtic people who lived in the British
islands at the time of Julius Caesar,
they were the descendants of the Yamna
males and the original women folk of the
region. So if Italy and Spain and Greece
have low Yamna ancestry, it means that
the genocide was only partially done
there. That's what it would mean. It
means that the original huntergather
folk who lived in Italy Greece um male
folk, it looks like many of them would
have survived the Yamna invasion and
their genetics continue. Uh does it mean
separate origins? Well, it depends on
what is the meaning of separate origins.
It depends on the time period we're
looking at. If you're looking at the
last 5,000 years, definitely separate
origins. If you're looking at the last
80,000 years, all common origins
pointing to Africa. So, it depends on
what lens you're looking at, what time
period you're looking at. But definitely
if you're looking at 5,000 year
perspective, definitely different
origins. Yes.
Godliness says some historians believe
the Rajput and Jat kings felt betrayed
by the Marata Empire. Hence they did not
support the Marata army in the third
battle of Anipad. Is this true? Uh and
so on. I am not an expert in this. I am
not interested in recent history. I have
not studied the Marata Empire in any
great detail. I am not competent to
answer questions about the Marata Empire
and the little petty rivalries that
existed in India at the time. I have no
interest in this period of history. It
is a majorly depressing period of Indian
history for me. It's maybe something
that's left over from my childhood
because in my childhood I used to stay
away from Indian history. I used to read
Greek history, Roman history, etc. blah
blah blah, Egyptian history, Chinese
history, world history. I would I I
would stay away from Indian history
because it was so depressing. It was a
history of defeats. And this entire time
period where you have Indians fighting
Indians and their maratas trying to
defeat the the muggles who have already
defeated the Rajpos before and all that.
I I have never really bothered to study
this in detail which is why I am not the
right person to answer this question and
I am not interested in these battles of
these ego battles. Marata versus Rajput
versus Jad versus whoever else versus
Gurjar versus Pratihar and God knows
what else. Indians they they they spend
their whole lives fighting this petty
little ego battles. They forget that we
are one people. Indians always
prioritize their subnational ancestry,
their subivilizational ancestry and
their subiviliz subivilizational
identities. This is the problem with
Indians. They have this great desire
from inside to keep fighting each other.
So I have no interest in this. I'm sorry
because I'm not the right person to
answer this question. Um godliness says
historical fact from Bible and core of
USIsrael alliance. Jesus's second coming
will only be possible if there will be a
third temple on the temple mount in the
holy holy city of Jerusalem. My views I
have no views. I stay out of this
matters. I have no idea. Very very
sorry. I have no idea. I have not
studied the Bible. The only time I read
the Bible was when I was stuck in a
hotel room when I was 8 years old and
they had this small little pocket Bible
and I had a whole day to to kill and the
TV TV was boring for that day for some
reason. So I read that little book and
that's the only time I read the Bible, a
pocket Bible and I have no recollection.
It was kind of an interesting story. Did
not have any effect on me by the way.
Yeah. Did not have any effect on me. Did
not convert me. Did not even tempt me to
convert. So failure. But yeah, I have no
idea about this. Sorry.
Pratt Dhana says Supreme Court criticize
the government for swinging Akbar bad
for showing Akbar bad. All right sir.
Okay. What can I say? All right. Noted.
Uh Akinta Anandan says Assyrian Queen
Seamis invaded India 800 BC but was
defeated by King Tabroatis near Indas.
Alexander later used the same route to
enter India. There is some story of an
Assyrian queen who tried to invade India
and who was defeated. All right. Yeah,
I've heard I've heard this but I've not
really studied this in detail. And
obviously if you are coming from the
west, you want to invade India from the
Persian route. Well, you have to take
the same route and it's a pretty open
territory, right? Uh eastern Persia,
it's all mostly deserted arid land and
it continues into Sind all the way.
There's nothing to stop you. It's
essentially it's an open road, open
land. you can just walk in. So yeah,
Alexander would have used the same route
to enter India. Adita Singh doesn't have
a question but All right, sir. Thank you
so much. I appreciate your contribution.
Thank you so much. Thank you so much,
sir.
Okay. Okay.
Um Adidi says, "Why are comments banned?
What did I do wrong?" Really? Why are
your comments banned? I'm seeing your
comment here. I have no idea. Are you
unable to put comments?
Um I can assure you that I have not
banned anyone's comments. Okay? If
YouTube is doing something I can't
control that. So this is a a foreign
platform. They will do what they want. I
am happy to take everybody's comments. I
don't why would your comments so I'm
sorry if you're facing any problems in
in putting questions but definitely not
me who has done that.
All right. Okay. Okay. So Vishala says
what? Oh, it's she's asking Aush, not
me. T you you take it offline. Mish
palad Aush. Okay.
All right, people. I think I'm going to
end it here. Thank you everybody for the
questions. It was a great live stream. I
had more questions, but I think I'll end
it over here. Two and a half hours. And
tomorrow we shall take questions about
geopolitics. So, those of you who have
questions about geopolitics, tomorrow is
the day. I'll take as many questions as
possible. Tomorrow only geopolitics. No
history. Tomorrow, only geopolitics.
Take care everybody. I look forward to
seeing you tomorrow. Keep asking
questions. Keep learning. Keep raising
your standards as always. And I'll see
you very soon. Bye-bye.